<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title xml:id="TSC">THE SPANISH CURATE</title>
        <author>John Fletcher</author>
        <author>Philip Massinger</author>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Edited and encoded by:</resp>
          <name xml:id="mim">Maria Isabel Maza</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Published by the Open Publishing Unit of The Pennsylvania State University Libraries.</publisher>
        <availability>
          <p>Attribution 4.0 International (CC BY 4.0)</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <seriesStmt>
        <title>The Digital Beaumont &amp; Fletcher (1647) Project</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor:</resp>
          <name xml:id="cmlb">Claire M.L. Bourne</name>
        </respStmt> 
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Project Manager:</resp>
          <name xml:id="hf">Heather Froehlich</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Text Encoding Consultant:</resp>
          <name xml:id="jr">John Russell</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Open Publishing Program Coordinator</resp>
          <name>Ally Laird</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Open Access Systems Developer</resp>
          <name xml:id="ag">Andrew Gearhart</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Graduate Assistants:</resp>
          <name>Taylor Hare</name>
          <name>David LeBlanc</name>
          <name>Danielle Ryle</name>
          <name>Lauren Cenci</name>
          <name>Maria Isabel Maza</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Annotator(s)</resp>
          <name xml:id="formerOwner">Former Owner - Author of Handwritten Annotations</name>
        </respStmt>
      </seriesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>Francis Beaumont</author>
            <author>John Fletcher</author>
            <title>Comedies and Tragedies Written by Francis Beavmont and Iohn Fletcher,
              Gentlemen. Never printed before, And now published by the Authours
              Originall Copies.</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Humprey Robinson</publisher>
              <publisher>the three Pidgeons</publisher>
              <publisher>Humphrey Moseley</publisher>
              <pubPlace>The Prince Armes in St. Pauls Church-yard</pubPlace>
              <date>1647</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier xml:id="psf">
            <country>The United States</country>
            <region>Pennsylvania</region>
            <institution>Pennsylvania State University</institution>
            <repository>Eberly Family Special Collections Library</repository>
            <collection>Emblem Books</collection>
            <msName>COMEDIES AND TRAGEDIES</msName> 
            <msName> 
              <rs>
                3083972
              </rs>
            </msName>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>This document is a simplified "true-to-text" XML version of <title>The Spanish Curate</title> based on Pennsylvania State University's annotated copy of the 1647
        Beaumont &amp; Fletcher first folio. Major textual elements and attributes have been captured based on how they appear in the folio. Whenever possible, editorial
        interventions have been minimalized or avoided entirely. This document is meant to serve as a pedagogical tool by which students of Early Modern literature can learn
        to construct edited XML versions of the play.</p>    
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          The Digital Beaumont &amp; Fletcher (1647) is a collaborative editorial project aimed at making many of the rarely edited—and, as a result, rarely taught—plays in the
          “Beaumont &amp; Fletcher” canon accessible to student readers and freely available online for classroom use. This project was inspired by the distinctive copy of Comedies
          and Tragedies Written by Francis Beavmont And Iohn Fletcher Gentlemen (1647) held by Penn State University's Eberly Family Special Collections Library. In addition to
          preserving evidence of ownership dating to as early as 1703, Penn State's copy of this printed play collection also includes three plays with handwritten marginalia,
          suggesting that the book might have been used to facilitate performance in the late seventeenth century. This project is also motivated by a desire to make the texts and
          other features of this book more widely known and readable. As a first step, the whole volume has now been fully digitized, thanks to the department of Preservation,
          Conservation, and Digitization at Penn State Libraries.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Provides details of editorial principles and practices applied during the encoding of a text</p>
        <correction>
          <p>
            This transcription copies almost exactly the text from Penn State's copy of the first folio. Moderniztions in certain letters were followed (I for J, VV for W, etc.) 
            Obivous errors were corrected (upside down letters (n for a u, I for l, etc.). Manuscript notes are included in the transcription, placed as closely as possible to the
            original placement on the page. For further details about editoral principles, please consult the project website. 
          </p>
        </correction>
        <normalization source="OED">
          <p>ALL words converted to Modern British spelling 
            following Oxford English Dictionary.</p>
        </normalization>
        <punctuation>
          <p>Punctuation was modernized to register full syntactical units.</p>
        </punctuation>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <handNotes>
        <handNote>
          <p>
            This edition of The Spanish Curate contains the manuscript notes found in the Penn State Libraries' copy of the 1647 folio. These manuscript notes are particually attentive to
            the performance of the play, and prepare actors for entrances and emphasize stage directions throughout the text. For more information on these manuscript notes, consult 
            the editorial principles and the introduction to <title>The Spanish Curate</title>.
          </p>
        </handNote>
      </handNotes>
      <langUsage>
        <p>chracters for marginal notes?</p>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="act4">
          <div xml:id="act4s1" type="scene" n="1">
            <head>
              <hi rend="italic">Actus Quartus Scæna Prima.</hi>
            </head>
            <stage type="entrance" place="center">Enter Don Henrique, Violante, Ascanio.</stage>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Hen.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Heare but my reasons,</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>O my patience heare 'em.</l>
                <l>Can cunning falshood colour an excuse?</l>
                <l>With any seeming shape of borrowed truth?</l>
                <l>Extenuate this wofull wrong, not error.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Hen.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>You gave consent that to defeat my brother</l>
                <l>I should take any course,</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>But not to make</l>
                <l>The cure more loathsome then the fowle disease:</l>
                <l>Was't not enough you took me to your bed,</l>
                <l>Tir'd with loose dalliance, and with emptie veines,</l>
                <l>All those abilities spent before and wasted,</l>
                <l>That could conferre the name of mother on me?</l>
                <l>But that (to perfect my account of sorrow)</l>
                <l>For my long barrenesse you must highten it</l>
                <l>By shewing to my face, that you were fruitfull</l>
                <l>Hug'd in the base embraces of another?</l>
                <l>If Solitude that dwelt beneath <placeName>my roofe</placeName>,</l>
                <l>And want of children was a torment to me</l>
                <l>What end my vexation to behold</l>
                <l>A bastard to upbraid me with my wants?</l>
                <l>And heare the name of father paid to ye</l>
                <l>Yet know my self no mother,</l>
                <l>What can I say?</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Hen.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>shall I confesse my fault and ask your pardon?</l>
                <l>Will that content ye?</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>If it could make void,</l>
                <l>What is confirm'd in Court, No, no, <persName><roleName>Don</roleName> Henrique</persName>,</l>
                <l>You shall know that I find my self abus'd,</l>
                <l>And adde to that I have a woman's anger.</l>
                <l>And while I look upon this Basilisk,</l>
                <l>Whose envious eyes hath blasted all my comforts</l>
                <l>Rest confident I'le study my dark ends,</l>
                <l>And not your pleasures,</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Asc.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l> Noble Lady, heare me,</l>
                <l>Not my Fathers son, but as your servant,</l>
                <l>Vouchsafe to heare me, for such in my duty,</l>
                <fw type="catch">I</fw>
                <pb n="TSC-016"
                  facs="https://digital.libraries.psu.edu/digital/collection/emblem/id/4396/rec/4"/>
                <fw type="pageNum">40</fw>
                <l>I ever will appeare: And far be it from</l>
                <l>My poore ambition, ever to looke on you,</l>
                <l>But with that reverence; which a slave stands bound</l>
                <l>To pay a worthy Mistris: I have heard</l>
                <l>That Dames of highest place, nay Queenes themselves,</l>
                <l>Disdaine not to be serv'd by such as are</l>
                <l>Of meanest Birth: and I shall be most happie,</l>
                <l>To be emploi'd when you please to command me</l>
                <l>Even in the coursest Office, as your Page,</l>
                <l>I can wayte on your trencher: : fill your wine</l>
                <l>Carry your pontafles, and be sometimes bless'd</l>
                <l>In all humilitie to touch your feete</l>
                <l>Or if that you esteeme that too much grace</l>
                <l>I can run by your Coach: observe your lookes</l>
                <l>And hope to gaine a fortune by my service,</l>
                <l>With your good favour, which now, as a Son,</l>
                <l>I dare not challenge</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>As a Son,</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Asc.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Forgive me</l>
                <l>I will forget the name, let it be death</l>
                <l>For me to call you Mother.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Still upbraided?</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Hen.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>No way left to appease you?</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>None: now heare me:</l>
                <l>Heare what I vow before the face of <placeName>heaven</placeName>,</l>
                <l>And if I breake it all plagues in this life,</l>
                <l>And those that after death are fear'd, fall on me</l>
                <l>While that this Bastard staies under <placeName>my rooffe</placeName>,</l>
                <l>Looke for no peace at <placeName>home</placeName>, for I renounce</l>
                <l>All Offices of a wife,</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Hen.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>What am I falne to?</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l rend="right">(howers</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I will not eate, nor sleepe with you and those</l>
                <l>Which I should spend in prayers for your health</l>
                <l>Shall be emploi'd in Curses,</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Hen.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Terrible,</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>All the day long, i'le be as tedious to you</l>
                <l>As lingring fevers, and i'le watch the nights,</l>
                <l>To ring alou'd your shame, and breake your sleepes</l>
                <l>Or if you doe but slumber, i'le appeare</l>
                <l>In the shape of all my wrongs, and like a fury</l>
                <l>Fright you to madnes, and if all this faile</l>
                <l>To worke out my revenge, I have friends and kinsmen,</l>
                <l>That will not sit downe tame with the disgrace</l>
                <l>That's offer'd to our noble familie</l>
                <l>In what I suffer,</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Hen.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>How am I devided</l>
                <l>Betweene the duties I owe as a Husband,</l>
                <l>And pietie of a Parent?</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Asc.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I am taught Sir</l>
                <l>By the instinct of nature that obedience</l>
                <l>Which bids me to prefer your peace of mind,</l>
                <l>Before those pleasures that are dearest to me</l>
                <l>Be wholy hers (my Lord) I quit all parts,</l>
                <l>That I may challenge: may you grow old together</l>
                <l>And no distast e're find you and before</l>
                <l>The Characters of age are printed on you</l>
                <l>May you see many Images of your selves,</l>
                <l>Though I, like some false Glasse, that's never look'd in</l>
                <l>Am cast a side, and broken from this hower</l>
                <l>(Unles invited, which I dare not hope for)</l>
                <l>I never will set my forbidden feete,</l>
                <l>Over your threshold: onely give me leave</l>
                <l>Though cast off to the <placeName>world</placeName>, to mention you,</l>
                <l>In my devotions 'tis all I sue for</l>
                <l>And so I take my last leave</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Hen.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Though I am</l>
                <l>Devoted to a wife nay allmost sol'd</l>
                <l>I slave to serve her pleasures, yet I cannot</l>
                <l>So part with all humanity, but I must</l>
                <l>Shew something of a Father: thou shalt not goe</l>
                <l>Unfurnish'd and unfriended too: take that</l>
                <l>To guard thee from necessities; may thy goodnes</l>
                <l>Deserve to be the heire of greater fortunes,</l>
                <l>Then thou wer't borne to. Scorne me not <persName>Violante</persName></l>
                <l>This banishment is a kind of civill death,</l>
                <l>And now, as it were at his Funerall</l><note type="mansNote" resp="#formerOwner" subtype="beReady">Le: Mil: ar:</note>
                <l>To shed a teare or two, one word more,</l>
                <l>And so farewell for ever: one word more,</l>
                <l>Though I must never see thee (my <persName>Ascanio</persName>)</l>
                <l>When this is spent (for so the Judge decreed)</l>
                <l>Send to me for supply: are you pleas'd now?</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Yes: I have cause: to see you howle and blubber</l>
                <l>At the parting of my torment, &amp; your shame <stage type="business" place="right">Bed ready wine,</stage></l>
                <l>'Tis well, proceed; supply his wants: doe doe: <stage type="business" place="right">table Standish &amp;</stage></l>
                <l>Let the great dowre I brought serve to maintain <stage type="business" place="right">Paper.</stage></l>
                <l>Your Bastards riots: send my Clothes and Jewells,</l>
                <l>To your old acquaintance, your deare dame his Mother</l>
                <l>Now you begin to melt, I know 'twill follow,</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Hen.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Is all I doe misconstrude?</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I will take</l>
                <l>A course to right my self a speeding one:</l>
                <l>By the bless'd Saints, I will; if I prove cruell</l>
                <l>To shame to see thy foolish pitty, taught me</l>
                <l>To loose my natural softness, keepe off from me</l>
                <l>Thy flateries are infectious, and i'le fle thee</l>
                <l>As I would doe a Leper.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Hen.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Let not fury</l>
                <l>Transport you so: you know I am your Creature.</l>
                <l>All love, but to your self, with him, hath left me</l>
                <l>I'le ioyne with you in any thing</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>In vaine</l>
                <l>I'le take mine owne waies, and will have no partners,</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Hen.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I will not crosse you,</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Doe not, they shall find</l>
                <l>That to a Woman of her hopes beguil'd</l>
                <l>A viper troad on, or an Aspick's mild.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <stage type="exit" place="right">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div><div xml:id="act4s2" type="scene" n="2">
            <head>
              <hi rend="italic">Scena Secunda.</hi>
            </head>
            <stage type="entrance" place="center">Enter Lopez Millanes Arsenio.</stage><note type="mansNote" resp="#formerOwner" subtype="crosshatchedlines">Cross-hatched lines.</note>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lop.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Sits the game there? I have you by mine order,</l>
                <l>I love <persName>Leandro</persName> for't</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Mil.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>But you must shew it</l>
                <l>In lending him your helpe, to gain him meane</l>
                <l>And opportunitie.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lop.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>He shall want nothing,</l>
                <l>I know my Advocate to a hayre, and what</l>
                <l>Will fetch him from his prayers, if he use any,</l>
                <l>I am honyed with the project: I would have him horn'd</l>
                <l>For a most precious Beast.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Ars.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>But you loose time;</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lop.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I am gon, instruct you <persName>Diego</persName>, and you will find him</l>
                <l>A sharpe and subtle knave, give him but hints</l>
                <l>And he will amplifie: Se all things ready</l>
                <l>I'll fetch him with a vengeance.—</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <stage type="exit" place="right">Exit.</stage>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Ars.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>If ye faile now,</l>
                <l>Wee'll give him over too,</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Mil.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Tush he is flesh'd</l>
                <l>And knowes what vaine to strike for his owne credit.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <fw type="catch" rend="italic">Ars.</fw>
            <pb n="TSC-017"
              facs="https://digital.libraries.psu.edu/digital/collection/emblem/id/4397/rec/4"/>
            <fw type="sig">G</fw>
            <fw type="pageNum">41</fw>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Ars.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>All things are ready.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Mil.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Then we shall have a merry Scene, ne're feare it.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <stage type="exit" place="right">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div xml:id="act4s3" type="scene" n="3">
            <head>
              <hi rend="italic">Scena Tertia.</hi>
            </head>
            <stage type="entrance" place="center">Enter Amaranta (with a note) and Moore.</stage>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Amar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Is thy Master gone out?</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Moore.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Even now, the Curat fetc'h'd him,</l>
                <l>About a serious businesss it seem'd,</l>
                <l>For he snatch'd up his Cloack, and brush'd his hat strait,</l>
                <l>Set his Band handsomely, and out he gallop'd.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Amar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>'Tis wil, 'tis very well, he went out (<persName>Egla</persName>.)</l>
                <l>As luckily, as one would say, goe Husband,</l>
                <l>He was call'd by providence: fling this short paper</l>
                <l>Into <persName>Leandro's</persName> <placeName>Cell</placeName>, and waken him,</l>
                <l>He is monstrous vexed, and musty, at my Chesse-play;</l>
                <l>But this shall supple him, when he has read it:</l>
                <l>Take your owne recreation for two houres,</l>
                <l>And hinder nothing.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Moore.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>If I doe, I'll hang for't.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <stage type="exit" place="right">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div xml:id="act4s4" type="scene" n="4">
            <head>
              <hi rend="italic">Scena quarta.</hi>
            </head>
            <stage type="entrance" place="center">Enter Octavio, Jacintha.</stage>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>If that you lov'd <persName>Ascanio</persName> for himselfe,</l>
                <l>And not your private ends, you rather should</l>
                <l>Blesse the faire opportunitie, that restores him</l>
                <l>To his Birth-right, and the Honours he was borne to,</l>
                <l>Then grieve at his good Fortune.</l><note type="mansNote" resp="#formerOwner" subtype="beReady">Jam: &amp; asca: be ready</note>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Jac.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Grieve <persName>Octavio</persName>?</l>
                <l>I would resigne my Essence, that he were</l>
                <l>As happy as my love could fashion him,</l>
                <l>Though every blessing that should fall on him,</l>
                <l>Might prove a curse to me, my sorrow springs</l>
                <l>Out of my feare, and doubt he is not safe.</l>
                <l>I am acquainted with <persName><roleName>Don</roleName> Henrique</persName>'s nature,</l>
                <l>And I have heard too much the fiery temper</l>
                <l>Of Madam <persName>Violante</persName>: can you thinke</l>
                <l>That she, that almost is at war with heaven</l>
                <l>For being barren, will with equall eyes</l>
                <l>Behold a Son of mine?</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>His Fathers care,</l>
                <l>That for the want of Issue, tooke him home,</l>
                <l>(Though with the forfeiture of his own fame)</l>
                <l>Will looke unto his safetie.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Jac.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Step-mothers</l>
                <l>Have many eyes, to find a way to mischiefe,</l>
                <l>Though blind to goodnesse.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <stage type="entrance" place="center">Enter Jamy and Ascanio.</stage><note type="mansNote" resp="#formerOwner" subtype="crosshatchedlines">Cross-hatched lines.</note>
            <sp> 
              <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Here comes <persName><roleName>Don</roleName> Jamy</persName>,</l>
                <l>And with him our <persName>Ascanio</persName>.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Jamy.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Good youth leave me,</l>
                <l>I know thou art forbid my company,</l>
                <l>And onely to be seene with me, will call on</l>
                <l>Thy Fathers anger.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Ars.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Sir, if that to serve you</l>
                <l>Could loose me any thing (as indeed it cannot)</l>
                <l>I still would follow you. Alas I was borne</l>
                <l>To doe you hurt but not to help my selfe,</l>
                <l>I was, for some particular end, tooke home,</l>
                <l>But am cast off againe.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Jam.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Is't possible?</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Asc.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>The Lady, whom my Father calls his wife</l>
                <l>Abhors my sight, is sick of me, and forc'd him</l>
                <l>To turne me out of dores.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Iac.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>By my best hopes</l>
                <l>I thanke her crueltie, for it comes neere</l>
                <l>A saving charitie.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Asc.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I am onely happy</l>
                <l>That yet I can relieve you, 'pray you share</l>
                <l>My Father's wondrous kind, and promises</l>
                <l>That I should be supplied: but sure the Lady</l>
                <l>Is a malitious woman, and I feare</l>
                <l>Meanes me no good.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <stage type="entrance" place="center">Enter Servant.</stage><note type="mansNote" resp="#formerOwner" subtype="crosshatchedlines">Cross-hatched lines.</note>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Iamy.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I am turn'd a stone with wonder,</l>
                <l>And know not what to thinke.</l><note type="mansNote" resp="#formerOwner" subtype="beReady">Lopez bartolus be ready</note>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>From my Lady,</l>
                <l>Your private eare and this—</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Iamy.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>New Miracles?</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>She sayes, if you dare make your selfe a Fortune,</l>
                <l>She will propose the meanes; My Lord <persName><roleName>Don</roleName> Henrique</persName></l>
                <l>Is now from home and she alone expects you,</l>
                <l>If you dare trust her so, if not despaire of</l>
                <l>A second offer,</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <stage type="exit" place="right">Exit.</stage>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Jam.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Though there were an Ambush</l>
                <l>Layd for my life, I,ll on and sound this secret,</l>
                <l>Retire thee (my <persName>Ascanio</persName>) with thy Mother:</l>
                <l>But stir not forth, some great designe's on foot,</l>
                <l>Fall what can fall, if e're the Sun be set,</l>
                <l>I see you not give me dead.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Asc.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>We will expect you,</l>
                <l>And those bless'd <persName>Angels</persName>, that love goodnesse, guard you.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <stage type="exit" place="right">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div xml:id="act4s5" type="scene" n="5">
            <head>
              <hi rend="italic">Scena Quinta.</hi>
            </head>
            <stage type="entrance" place="center">Enter Lopez and Bartolus.</stage><note type="mansNote" resp="#formerOwner" subtype="crosshatchedlines">Cross-hatched lines.</note>
              <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Is't possible he should be rich?</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lop.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Most possible,</l>
                <l>He hath bin long, though he has but little gettings,</l>
                <l>Drawing together Sir.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Accounted a poore Sexton,</l>
                <l>Honest poore <persName>Diego</persName>,</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lop.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I assure ye, a close Fellow,</l>
                <l>Both close, and scraping, and that fills the bags, Sir,</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>A notable good Fellow too?</l><note type="mansNote" resp="#formerOwner" subtype="crosshatchedlines">Cross-hatched lines.</note>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lopez.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Sometimes, Sir, <stage type="business" place="right">Diego ready in Bed, wine, cup.</stage></l>
                <l>When he hop'd to drink a man into a surfeit,</l>
                <l>That he might gaine by his Grave.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>So many thousands?</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lop.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Heaven knowes what.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>'Tis strange,</l>
                <l>,Tis very strange; but we see by endeavour,</l>
                <l>And honest labour—</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lop.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l><persName>Milo</persName> by continuance</l>
                <l>Grew from a silly Calfe (with your worships reverence)</l>
                <l>To carry a Bull from a penny, to a pound, Sir,</l>
                <l>And from a pound, to many: 'tis the progresse.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Ye say true, but he lov'd to feed well also,</l>
                <l>And that me-thinks—</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lop.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>From another mans Trencher, Sir,</l>
                <l>And there he found it season'd with small charge:</l>
                <l>There he would play the Tyrant, and would devoure ye</l>
                <l>More then the <placeName>Graves</placeName> he made at home he liv'd</l>
                <l>Like a Camelion, suckt th'Ayre of misery, <stage type="business" place="right">Table out Stan-</stage></l>
                <l>And grew fat by th'Brewis of an Eg-shel, <stage type="business" place="right">dish paper, stools.</stage></l>
                <fw type="catch">Would</fw>
                <pb n="TSC-018"
                  facs="https://digital.libraries.psu.edu/digital/collection/emblem/id/4398/rec/4"/>
                <fw type="pageNum">42</fw>
                <note type="mansNote" resp="#formerOwner" subtype="beReady">[...]asenio &amp; parishioners</note><l>Would smell a Cooks shop, and goe home and surfeit,</l>
                <l>And be a moneth in fasting out that Fever.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l rend="italic">(ye?</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>These are very good Symptomes: do's he lye so sick, say</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lop.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Oh, very sick.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>And chosen me Executor?</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lop.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Onely one Worship.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>No hope of his amendment?</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lop.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>None, that we find.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>He hath no kinsmen neither?</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lop.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>'Truth, very few.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>His mind will be the quieter,</l>
                <l>What Doctors has he?</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lop.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>There's none sir, he believes in.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>They are but needlesse things, in such exteremities.</l>
                <l>Who drawes the good-man's will?</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lop.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Marry that doe I, Sir.</l>
                <l>And to my griefe.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Griefe will doe little now, Sir,</l>
                <l>Draw it to your comfort, Friend, and as I counsell ye,</l>
                <l>An honest man, but such men live not alwayes</l>
                <l>Who are about him?</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lop.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Many now he is passing,</l>
                <l>That would pretend to his love, yes, and some gentlemen</l>
                <l>That would faine counsell him, and be of his kindred;</l>
                <l>Rich men can want no heires, Sir.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>They doe ill,</l>
                <l>Indeed they doe, to trouble him: very ill, Sir,</l>
                <l>But we shall take a care.</l><note type="mansNote" resp="#formerOwner" subtype="crosshatchedlines">Cross-hatched lines.</note>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <note type="mansNote" resp="#formerOwner" subtype="crosshatchedlines">Cross-hatched lines.</note><stage type="entrance" place="center">Enter Diego (in a bed) Millanes, Arsenio, and Parishioners.</stage>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lop.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Will ye come neare, Sir,</l>
                <l>'Pray ye bring him out; Now ye may see in what state:</l>
                <l>Give him fresh ayre.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <stage type="business" place="right">Bed thrust out.</stage>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I am sorry Neighbour <persName>Diego</persName>,</l>
                <l>To find ye in so weake a state.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Die.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Ye are welcome,</l>
                <l>But I am fleeting, Sir.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Me-thinkes he looks well,</l>
                <l>His colour fresh, and strong, his eyes are chearfull.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lop.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>A glimmering before death 'tis nothing els, Sir,</l>
                <l>Do you see how he fumbles with the sheet? do ye note that</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Di.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>My learned Sir 'pray ye sit: I am bold to send for ye,</l>
                <l>To take care of what I leave.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lop.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Doe you heare that?</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Ars.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Play the knave finely.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Die.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>So I will, I warrant ye,</l>
                <l>And carefully.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>'Pray ye doe not trouble him,</l>
                <l>You see he's weake and has a wandring fancie.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Di.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>My honest Neighbours, weep not, I must leave ye,</l>
                <l>I cannot alwayes beare ye company,</l>
                <l>We must drop still there is no remedie:</l>
                <l>'Pray ye Master C urat, will ye write my Testament,</l>
                <l>And write it largely it may be remembered</l>
                <l>And be witnesse to my Legacies good Gentlemen;</l>
                <l>Your worship I doe make my full Executor,</l>
                <l>You are a man of wit and understanding:</l>
                <l>Give me a cup of wine to raise my Spirits,</l>
                <l>For I speake low: I would before these Neighbours</l>
                <l>Have ye to sweare (Sir) that you will see it executed,</l>
                <l>And what I give, let equally be rendered</l>
                <l>For my soules health.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I vow it truly, Neighbours,</l>
                <l>Let not that trouble ye before all these</l>
                <l>Once more I give my Oath.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Di.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Then set me higher,</l>
                <l>And pray ye come neare me all.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lop.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>We are ready for ye.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Mil.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Now spur the Asse, and get our friend time.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Die.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>First then,</l>
                <l>After I have given my Body to the wormes</l>
                <l>(For they must be serv'd first, they are seldome cozen'd)</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lop.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Remember your <placeName>Parish</placeName>, Neighbour.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Di.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>You speake truly,</l>
                <l>I doe remember it, a lewd vile <placeName>Parish</placeName>,</l>
                <l>And pray it may be mended: To the Poore of it,</l>
                <l>(Which is to all the <placeName>Parish</placeName>) I give nothing,</l>
                <l>For nothing, unto nothing, is most naturall,</l>
                <l>Yet leave as much space, as will build a <placeName>Hospitall</placeName>,</l>
                <l>Their children may pray for me.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>What doe you give to it?</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Die.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Set downe two thousand Duckets,</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>'Tis a good gift,</l>
                <l>And will be long remembered.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Die.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>To your worship,</l>
                <l>(Because you must take paines to see all finish'd)</l>
                <l>I give two thousand more, it may be three, Sir,</l>
                <l>A poore gratuitie for your paines-taking.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>These are large summes;</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lop.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Nothing to him that has 'em.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Die.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>To my old Master Vicar I give five hundred,</l>
                <l>(Five hundred, and five hundred, are too few Sir)</l>
                <l>But there be more to serve.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>This fellow coynes sure.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Di.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Give me some more drink. Pray ye buy Books, buy<lb rend="turnunder"/>Books,</l>
                <l>You have a learned head stuffe it with <placeName>Libraries</placeName>,</l>
                <l>And understand 'em, when you have done, 'tis Justice,</l>
                <l>Run not the Parish mad with Controversies,</l>
                <l>Nor preach not Abstinence to longing women,</l>
                <l>'Twill budge the bottoms of their consciences:</l>
                <l>I would give the <placeName>Church</placeName> new Organs, but I prophecie</l>
                <l>The Church-wardens would quickly pipe'em out o'the'<placeName>Pa<lb rend="turnunder"/>rish,</placeName>-</l>
                <l>Two hundred Duckets more to mend the chancel,</l>
                <l>And to paint true Orthographie, as many,</l>
                <l>They write <hi rend="italic" xml:lang="la">Sunt</hi> with a <hi rend="italic">C</hi> which is abominable,</l>
                <l>'Pray you set that downe, to poore Maidens marriages.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I that's wel thought of, what's your wil in that point?</l>
                <l>A meritorious thing.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>No end of this will?</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Di.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I give <hi rend="italic" xml:lang="la">per annum</hi> two hundred ells of Lockram,</l>
                <l>That there be no strait dealings in their Linnens,</l>
                <l>But the Sayles cut according to their Burthens;</l>
                <l>To all Bell-Ringers, I bequeath new Ropes,</l>
                <l>And let them use 'em at their owne discretions.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Ars.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>You may remember us.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Di.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I doe, good Gentlemen,</l>
                <l>And I bequeath ye both good carefull Surgeons</l>
                <l>A Legacy, you have need of, more then money,</l>
                <l>I know you want good Diets and good Lotions,</l>
                <l>And in your pleasures good take heed.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lop</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>He raves now.</l>
                <l>But 'twill be quickly off,</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Di.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I doe bequeath ye</l>
                <l>Commodities of pins: browne papers: pack-threds,</l>
                <l>Rost proke, &amp; puddings: Ginger-bread, &amp; Jewes-trumps;</l>
                <l>Of penny Pipes, and mouldy Pepper: take 'em,</l>
                <l>Take 'em even where you please and be cozen'd with 'em,</l>
                <l>I should bequeath ye Executions also,</l>
                <l>But those I'll leave to th'Law.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lop.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Now he growes temperate.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>You will give no more?</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Di.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I am loth to give more from ye,</l>
                <fw type="catch">Because</fw>
                <pb n="TSC-019"
                  facs="https://digital.libraries.psu.edu/digital/collection/emblem/id/4399/rec/4"/>
                <fw type="sig">G2</fw>
                <fw type="pageNum">43</fw>
                <l>Because I know you will have a care to execute</l>
                <l>Onely, to pious uses, Sir, a little.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>If he be worth all these, I am made for ever,</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Die.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I give to fatall Dames, that spin mens threds out,</l>
                <l>And poore distressed Damsells, that are militant</l>
                <l>As members of our owne Afflictions,</l>
                <l>A hundred Crowns to buy warm tubbs to worke in,</l>
                <l>I give five hundred pounds to buy a <placeName>Church-yard</placeName>,</l>
                <l>A spacious <placeName>Church-yard</placeName>, to lay Theeves and knaves in,</l>
                <l>Rich men, and honest men, take all the roome up.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lop.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Are ye not weary?</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Di.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Never of well-doing.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>These are mad Legacies.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Die.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>They were got as madly;</l>
                <l>My Sheep, and Oxen, and my moveables,</l>
                <l>My Plate, and Jewells, and five hundred Acres;</l>
                <l>I have no heires.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>This cannot be, 'tis Monstrous.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Die.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Three Ships at <placeName>Sea</placeName> too.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>You have made me full Executor.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Di.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Full, full, and totall, would I had more to give ye</l>
                <l>But these may serve an honest mind.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Ye say true,</l>
                <l>A very honest mind, and make it rich too;</l>
                <l>Rich, wondrous rich, but where shall I raise these monys,</l>
                <l>About <placeName>your house</placeName>? I see no such great promises;</l>
                <l>Where shall I find these summes?</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Die.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Even where you please Sir,</l>
                <l>You are wise and provident, and know businesse</l>
                <l>Ev'n raise 'em where you shal think good, I am reasonable</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Thinke good? will that raise thousands?</l>
                <l>What doe you make me?</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Di.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>You have sworn to see it done, that's all my comfort.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Where I please? this is pack'd sure to disgrace me.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Di.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>You are just, and honest, and I know you will doe it,</l>
                <l>Ev'n where you please, for you know where the wealth is.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I am abused, betrayed, I am laugh'd at, scorn'd,</l>
                <l>Baffel'd, and boared, it seemes.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Ars.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>No, no, ye are fooled.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lop.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Most finely fooled, and handsomely, and neatly,</l>
                <l>Such cunning Masters must be fooled sometimes, Sir,</l>
                <l>And have their worships noses wiped, 'tis healthfull,</l>
                <l>We are but quit: you foole us of our moneys</l>
                <l>In every Cause, in every Quiddit wipe us.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Di.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Ha, ha, ha, ha, some more drink, for my heart, Gentle<lb rend="turnunder"/>men</l>
                <l>This merry Lawyer—ha,ha,ha,ha, this Scholler—</l>
                <l>I thinke this fitt will cure me: this Executor—</l>
                <l>I shall laugh out my Lungs.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>This is derision above sufferance, villany</l>
                <l>Plotted, and set against me.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Die.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Faith 'tis knavery,</l>
                <l>In troth I must confesse, thou art fooled indeed, Lawyer.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Mil.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Did you thinke, had this man been rich—</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>'Tis well, Sir.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Mil.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>He would have chosen such a Wolfe, a Cancker,</l>
                <l>A Maggot-pate, to be his whole Executor.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lop.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>A Lawyer, that entangles all mens honesties,</l>
                <l>And lives like a Spider in a Cobweb lurking,</l>
                <l>And catching at all Flies, that passe his pitt-falls?</l>
                <l>Puts powder to all States, to make 'em caper?</l>
                <l>Would he trust you?</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Die.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Doe you deserve? I find, Gentlemen,</l>
                <l>This Cataplasme of a well cozen'd Lawyer</l>
                <l>Laid to my stomach lenifies my Fever,</l>
                <l>Me-thinkes I could eat now and walke a little.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I am asham'd to feele how flat I am cheated,</l>
                <l>How grossely, and malitiously made a May-game,</l>
                <l>A damned Trick; my wife, my wife, some Rascall:</l>
                <l>My credit, and my wife, some lustfull villaine,</l>
                <l>Some Bawd, some Rogue,</l><note type="mansNote" resp="#formerOwner" subtype="beReady">Amararan &amp; Leandro be ready</note>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Ars.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Some craftie Foole has found ye:</l>
                <l>This 'tis Sir, to teach ye to be too busie,</l>
                <l>To covet all the gaines, and all the rumours.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lop.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>We did this, but to vex your fine officiousnesse.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Good yeild ye and go'd thank ye: I am fooled, gen<lb rend="turnunder"/>(tlemen;-</l>
                <l>The Lawyer is an Asse, I doe confesse it,</l>
                <l>A weak dull shallow Asse: good even to your worships:</l>
                <l>Vicar, remember Vicar, Rascall remember,</l>
                <l>Thou notable rich Rascall.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Die.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I doe remember, Sir,</l>
                <l>'Pray ye stay a little, I have ev'n two Legacies</l>
                <l>To make your mouth up, sir.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Remember Varletts,</l>
                <l>Quake &amp; remember, Rouges; I have brine for your But<lb rend="turnover"/>tocks. <stage type="exit" place="right">Ex.</stage></l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lop.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Oh how he frets, and fumes now like a dunghill.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Di.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>His gall containes fine stuffe now to make poysons,</l>
                <l>Rare damned stuffe.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Ars.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Let's after him, and still vex him,</l>
                <l>And take my Friend off: by this time he has prosper'd,</l>
                <l>He cannot loose this deere time: 'tis impossible.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Mil.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Well <persName>Diego</persName>, thou hast done.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lop.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Hast done it daintily.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Mil.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>And shalt be as well paid, Boy—</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Ars.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Goe, let's crucifie him.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <stage type="exit" place="right">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div xml:id="act4s6" type="scene" n="6">
            <head>
              <hi rend="italic">Scæne Sexta.</hi>
            </head>
            <stage type="entrance" place="center">Enter Amaranta, Leandro.</stage><note type="mansNote" resp="#formerOwner" subtype="crosshatchedlines">Cross-hatched lines.</note>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lea.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I have told ye all my story, and how desperately.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Am.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I doe believe: let's walke on, time is pretious,</l>
                <l>Not to be spent in words, here no more wooing,</l>
                <l>The open Ayre's an enemy to Lovers, <stage type="business" place="right">Pewter ready</stage></l>
                <l>Doe as I tell ye. <stage type="business" place="right">for noyse.</stage></l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lea.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I'll doe any thing,</l><note type="mansNote" resp="#formerOwner" subtype="crosshatchedlines">Cross-hatched lines.</note>
                <l>I am so over-joy'd, I'll fly to serve ye.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Am.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Take your joy moderately, as it is ministred,</l>
                <l>And as the cause invites: that man's a foole</l><note type="mansNote" resp="#formerOwner" subtype="beReady">bartolus be ready</note>
                <l>That at the sight o'th'Bond, dances and leapes,</l>
                <l>Then is the true joy, when the money comes.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lea.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>You cannot now deny me.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker> rend="italic">Am.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Nay, you know not,</l>
                <l>Women have crotchets, and strange fits.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lea.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>You shall not.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Am.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Hold ye to that and sweare it confidently,</l>
                <l>Then I shall make a scruple to deny ye:</l>
                <l>'Pray ye let's step in, and see a friend of mine,</l>
                <l>The weather's sharp: we'll stay but halfe an houre,</l>
                <l>We may be miss'd els: a <placeName>private fine house</placeName> 'tis, Sir,</l>
                <l>And we may find many good welcomes.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lea.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Doe Lady,</l>
                <l>Doe happy Lady.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Am.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>All your mind's of doing,</l>
                <l>You must be modester.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lea.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I will be any thing.—</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <stage type="exit" place="right">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div xml:id="act4s7" type="scene" n="7">
            <head>
              <hi rend="italic">Scæna Septima.</hi>
            </head>
            <stage type="entrance" place="center">Enter Bartolus.</stage><note type="mansNote" resp="#formerOwner" subtype="crosshatchedlines">Cross-hatched lines.</note>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Open the dores, and give me roome to chafe in</l>
                <l>Mine owne <placeName>romme</placeName>, and my liberty: why Maid there,</l>
                <fw type="catch">Open</fw>
                <pb n="TSC-020"
                  facs="https://digital.libraries.psu.edu/digital/collection/emblem/id/4400/rec/4"/>
                <fw type="pageNum">44</fw>
                <note type="mansNote" resp="#formerOwner" subtype="beReady">lo: Ar: Mill: Diego be ready</note><l>Open, I say, and doe not anger me,</l>
                <l>I am subject to much fury: when ye dish-clout?</l>
                <l>When doe ye come? a sleepe, ye lazie hell-hound?</l>
                <l>Nothing intended, but your ease, and eating?</l>
                <l>No body here? why wife, why wife? why jewell?</l>
                <l>No tongue to answer me? 'pree'thee (good Pupill)</l>
                <l>Dispence a little with thy careful study,</l>
                <l>And step to th' doore, and let me in; nor he neither?</l>
                <l>Ha! not at's study? nor asleepe? nor no-body?</l>
                <l>I'll make ye heare: the house of Ignorance,</l>
                <l>No sound inhabitants here: I have a key yet</l>
                <l>That commands all: I feare I am metamorphiz'd.</l><note type="mansNote" resp="#formerOwner" subtype="crosshatchedlines">Cross-hatched lines.</note>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <note type="mansNote" resp="#formerOwner" subtype="crosshatchedlines">Cross-hatched lines.</note><stage type="entrance" place="center">Enter Lopez, Arsenio, Milanes, Diego.</stage>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lop.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>He keepes his fury still, and may doe mischiefe.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Mil.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>He shalbe hang'd first, we'll be sticklers there, boyes</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Di.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>The hundred thousand Dreams now, that posses him</l>
                <l>Of jealousie, and of revenge, and frailtie</l>
                <l>Of drawing Bills against us, and Petitions.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lop.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>And casting what his credit shall recover.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Mil.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Let him cast till his Maw came up, we care not.</l>
                <l>You shall be still secured.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp><stage type="business" place="center">A great noyse within.</stage>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Die.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>We'll pay him home then;</l>
                <l>Hark what a noyse he keeps within?</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lop.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Certaine</l>
                <note type="mansNote" resp="#formerOwner" subtype="crosshatchedlines">Cross-hatched lines.</note><l>H'as set his Chimneys o' fire, or the divell roars there.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Di.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>The Codixes o'th' Law are broke loose,</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Ars.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>He's fighting sure,</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Di.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I'll tell ye that immediatly—.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <stage type="exit" place="center">Exit.</stage>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Mil.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Or doing some strange out-rage on himselfe.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Ars.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Hang him, he dares not be so valiant.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <note type="mansNote" resp="#formerOwner" subtype="crosshatchedlines">Cross-hatched lines.</note><stage type="entrance" place="center">Enter Diego.</stage>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Di.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>There's no body at home and he chases like a Lyon,</l>
                <note type="mansNote" resp="#formerOwner" subtype="beReady">Ama Leandro be ready</note><l>And stinkes withall.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp><stage type="business" place="right">Noyse still.</stage>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lop.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>No body?</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Di.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Not a creature,</l>
                <l>Nothing within, but he and his Law-tempest,</l>
                <l>The Ladles, dishes, kettles, how they fly all?</l>
                <l>And how the Glasses through the <placeName>Roomes</placeName>?</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <note type="mansNote" resp="#formerOwner" subtype="crosshatchedlines">Cross-hatched lines.</note><stage type="entrance" place="right">Enter Bartolus.</stage>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Ars.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>My friends sure</l>
                <l>Has got her out, and now he has made an end on't.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lop.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>See where the <placeName>Sea</placeName> comes? how it foams &amp; brussels?</l>
                <l>The great Leviathan o'th' Law, how it tumbles?</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Made every way an Asse? abus'd on all sides?</l>
                <l>And from all quarters. people come to laugh at me?</l>
                <l>Rise like a Comet, to be wonder'd at?</l>
                <l>A horrid Comet, for Boyes tongues, and Ballads?</l>
                <l>I will run from my wits.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <note type="mansNote" resp="#formerOwner" subtype="crosshatchedlines">Cross-hatched lines.</note><stage type="entrance" place="center">Enter Amaranta, Leandro.</stage>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Ars.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Doe, doe (good Lawyer)</l>
                <l>And from thy money too, then thou wilt be quiet.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Mil.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Here she comes home: now mark the salutations;</l>
                <l>How like an Asse my friend goes?</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Ars.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>She has pull'd his eares downe.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Now, what sweet voyage? to what <placeName>Garden</placeName>, Lady?</l>
                <l>Or to what <placeName>Cosens house</placeName>?</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Am.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Is this my welcome?</l>
                <l>I cannot goe to <placeName>Church</placeName>, but thus I am scandall'd,</l>
                <l>Use no devotion for my soule, but Gentlemen—</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>To <placeName>Church</placeName>?</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Am.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Yes, and ye keep sweet youths to wait upon me,</l>
                <l>Sweet bred-up youths, to be a credit to me.</l>
                <l>There's your delight againe, pray take him to ye,</l>
                <l>He never comes neare me more to debase me.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Ba.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>How's this? how's this? good wife, how has he wrongd <lb rend="turnover"/>ye?</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Am.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I am faine to drive him like a sheep before me,</l>
                <l>I blush to thinke how people fleere, and scorn'd me,</l>
                <l>Others have handsome men, that know behaviour,</l>
                <l>Place, and observance: this silly thing knowes nothing,</l>
                <l>Cannot tell ten; Let every Rascall justle me,</l>
                <l>And still I push'd him on, as he had bin comming.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Ha! did ye push him on? is he so stupid?</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Am.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>When others were attentive to the Priest,</l>
                <l>Good devout Gentleman, then fell he fast</l>
                <l>Fast, sound asleep: then first began the Bag-pipes</l>
                <l>The severall stops on's nose, made a rare musick,</l>
                <l>A rare and lowd, and those plaid many an Antheme</l>
                <l>Put out of that, he fell strait into dreaming.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Ars.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>As cunning as she is sweet; I like this carriage.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>What did he then?</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Am.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Why then he talked in his Sleep too,</l>
                <l>Nay, I'll divulge your morall vertues (sheeps-face)</l>
                <l>And talk'd aloude, that every eare was fixt to him:</l>
                <l>Did not I suffer (doe you thinke) in this time?</l>
                <l>Talk of your bawling Law, of appellations</l>
                <l>Of Declarations, and Excommunications:</l>
                <l>Warrants, the Executions: and such <persName>divells</persName></l>
                <l>That drove all the Gentlemen out o'th'<placeName>Church</placeName>, by hur<lb rend="turnover"/>ryes</l>
                <l>With execrable oaths, they would never come there again</l>
                <l>Thus am I serv'd, and man'd.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lea.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I pray ye forgive me,</l>
                <l>I must confesse I am not fit to wait upon ye:</l>
                <l>Alas, I was brought up—</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Am.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>To be an Asse,</l>
                <l>A Lawyers Asse, to carry Bookes, and Buckrams.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>But what did you at <placeName>Church</placeName>?</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lop.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>At <placeName>Church</placeName>, did ye aske her?</l>
                <l>Doe you heare gentlemen, doe you mark the question?</l>
                <l>Because you are halfe an heretique your selfe, Sir,</l>
                <l>Would ye breed her too? this shall to the Inquisition,</l>
                <l>A pious Gentlewoman, reprov'd for praying?</l>
                <l>I'll see this filed, and you shall heare further, Sir.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Ars.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Ye have an ill heart.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lop.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>It shall be found out Gentlemen,</l>
                <l>There be those youths will search it.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Die.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>You are warme Signiour,</l>
                <l>But a Faggot will warme ye better: we are witnesses.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lop.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Enough to hang him, doe not doubt.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Mil.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Nay certaine,</l>
                <l>I doe beleeve has rather no Religion.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lop.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l rend="right">(<placeName>Church</placeName>, sir?</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lop.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>That must be knowne too, because shee goes to</l>
                <l><hi rend="italic" xml:lang="la">O monstrum informe ingens</hi>!</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Die.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Let him goe on, sir,</l>
                <l>His wealth will build a <placeName>Nunnery</placeName>, a faire one,</l>
                <l>And this good Lady, when he is hang'd, and rotten,</l>
                <l>May there be Abbesse.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>You are cozend, honest Gentlemen,</l>
                <l>I doe not forbid the use, but the forme, marke me.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lop.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Forme? what doe ye make of Forme?</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>They will undoe me,</l>
                <l>Sweare, as I oft have done, and so betray me;</l>
                <l>I must make faire way, and hereafter, Wife,</l>
                <l>You are welcome home, &amp; henceforth take your pleasure,</l>
                <l>Goe, when ye shall thinke fit, I will not hinder ye,</l>
                <l>My eyes are open now, and I see my e[]rour,</l>
                <l>My shame, as great as that, but I must hide it.</l>
                <l>The whole conveyance now I smell, but <hi rend="italic" xml:lang="es">Basta</hi>,</l>
                <l>Another time must serve: you see us friends, now</l>
                <l>Heartily friends, and no more chiding (gentlemen)</l>
                <l>I have bin too foolish, I confesse, no more words,</l>
                <l>No more (sweet wife.)</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <fw type="catch" rend="italic">Am.</fw>
            <pb n="TSC-021"
              facs="https://digital.libraries.psu.edu/digital/collection/emblem/id/4401/rec/4"/>
            <fw type="pageNum">45</fw>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Am.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>You know my easie nature</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Goe get ye in: you see she has bin angry:</l>
                <l>Forebeare her fight a while and time will pacify.</l>
                <l>And learne to be more bold.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lea.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I would I could,</l>
                <l>I will doe all I am able.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp><stage type="exit" place="right">Exit.</stage>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Doe <persName>Leandro</persName>.</l><note type="mansNote" resp="#formerOwner" subtype="other">Act</note>
                <l>We will not part, but friends of all hands.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lop.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Well said,</l>
                <l>Now ye are reasonable, we can looke on ye,</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Ye have ierckt me: but for all that I forgive ye</l>
                <l>Forgive ye hartily, and doe invite ye</l>
                <l>Tomorrow to a Breakfast, I make but seldome</l>
                <l>But now we will be merry.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Ars.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Now ye are friendly,</l>
                <l>Your doggednes and nigardize flung from ye,</l>
                <l>And now we will come to ye</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Give me your hands, all;</l>
                <l>You shall be wellcome hartily.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lop.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>We will be,</l>
                <l>For wee'll eate hard</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>The harder, the more wellcome,</l>
                <l>And till the morning farewell; I have busines.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <stage type="exit" place="right">Exit.</stage>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Mil.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Farewell good bountiful <persName rend="itatlic">Bartolus</persName> 'tis a brave wench</l>
                <l>A sudaine witty Theif, and worth all service:</l>
                <l>Goe wee'll all goe, and crucifie the Lawyer,</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Die.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I'll clap foure tire of teeth into my mouth more</l>
                <l>But I will grind his substance.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Ars.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Well <persName>Leandro</persName>,</l>
                <l>Thou hast had a strange voyage, but I hope</l>
                <l>Thou rid'st now in safe <placeName>harbour</placeName>,</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Mil.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Lets goe drinke, Friends,</l>
                <l>And laugh alou'd at all our merry may-games</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lop.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>A match, a match 'twill whet our stomachs better.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <stage type="exit" place="right">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
      </div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
