<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title xml:id="TSC">THE SPANISH CURATE</title>
        <author>John Fletcher</author>
        <author>Philip Massinger</author>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Edited and encoded by:</resp>
          <name xml:id="mim">Maria Isabel Maza</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Published by the Open Publishing Unit of The Pennsylvania State University Libraries.</publisher>
        <availability>
          <p>Attribution 4.0 International (CC BY 4.0)</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <seriesStmt>
        <title>The Digital Beaumont &amp; Fletcher (1647) Project</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor:</resp>
          <name xml:id="cmlb">Claire M.L. Bourne</name>
        </respStmt> 
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Project Manager:</resp>
          <name xml:id="hf">Heather Froehlich</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Text Encoding Consultant:</resp>
          <name xml:id="jr">John Russell</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Open Publishing Program Coordinator</resp>
          <name>Ally Laird</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Open Access Systems Developer</resp>
          <name xml:id="ag">Andrew Gearhart</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Graduate Assistants:</resp>
          <name>Taylor Hare</name>
          <name>David LeBlanc</name>
          <name>Danielle Ryle</name>
          <name>Lauren Cenci</name>
          <name>Maria Isabel Maza</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Annotator(s)</resp>
          <name xml:id="formerOwner">Former Owner - Author of Handwritten Annotations</name>
        </respStmt>
      </seriesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>Francis Beaumont</author>
            <author>John Fletcher</author>
            <title>Comedies and Tragedies Written by Francis Beavmont and Iohn Fletcher,
              Gentlemen. Never printed before, And now published by the Authours
              Originall Copies.</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Humprey Robinson</publisher>
              <publisher>the three Pidgeons</publisher>
              <publisher>Humphrey Moseley</publisher>
              <pubPlace>The Prince Armes in St. Pauls Church-yard</pubPlace>
              <date>1647</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier xml:id="psf">
            <country>The United States</country>
            <region>Pennsylvania</region>
            <institution>Pennsylvania State University</institution>
            <repository>Eberly Family Special Collections Library</repository>
            <collection>Emblem Books</collection>
            <msName>COMEDIES AND TRAGEDIES</msName> 
            <msName> 
              <rs>
                3083972
              </rs>
            </msName>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>This document is a simplified "true-to-text" XML version of <title>The Spanish Curate</title> based on Pennsylvania State University's annotated copy of the 1647
        Beaumont &amp; Fletcher first folio. Major textual elements and attributes have been captured based on how they appear in the folio. Whenever possible, editorial
        interventions have been minimalized or avoided entirely. This document is meant to serve as a pedagogical tool by which students of Early Modern literature can learn
        to construct edited XML versions of the play.</p>    
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          The Digital Beaumont &amp; Fletcher (1647) is a collaborative editorial project aimed at making many of the rarely edited—and, as a result, rarely taught—plays in the
          “Beaumont &amp; Fletcher” canon accessible to student readers and freely available online for classroom use. This project was inspired by the distinctive copy of Comedies
          and Tragedies Written by Francis Beavmont And Iohn Fletcher Gentlemen (1647) held by Penn State University's Eberly Family Special Collections Library. In addition to
          preserving evidence of ownership dating to as early as 1703, Penn State's copy of this printed play collection also includes three plays with handwritten marginalia,
          suggesting that the book might have been used to facilitate performance in the late seventeenth century. This project is also motivated by a desire to make the texts and
          other features of this book more widely known and readable. As a first step, the whole volume has now been fully digitized, thanks to the department of Preservation,
          Conservation, and Digitization at Penn State Libraries.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Provides details of editorial principles and practices applied during the encoding of a text</p>
        <correction>
          <p>
            This transcription copies almost exactly the text from Penn State's copy of the first folio. Moderniztions in certain letters were followed (I for J, VV for W, etc.) 
            Obivous errors were corrected (upside down letters (n for a u, I for l, etc.). Manuscript notes are included in the transcription, placed as closely as possible to the
            original placement on the page. For further details about editoral principles, please consult the project website. 
          </p>
        </correction>
        <normalization source="OED">
          <p>ALL words converted to Modern British spelling 
            following Oxford English Dictionary.</p>
        </normalization>
        <punctuation>
          <p>Punctuation was modernized to register full syntactical units.</p>
        </punctuation>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <handNotes>
        <handNote>
          <p>
            This edition of The Spanish Curate contains the manuscript notes found in the Penn State Libraries' copy of the 1647 folio. These manuscript notes are particually attentive to
            the performance of the play, and prepare actors for entrances and emphasize stage directions throughout the text. For more information on these manuscript notes, consult 
            the editorial principles and the introduction to <title>The Spanish Curate</title>.
          </p>
        </handNote>
      </handNotes>
      <langUsage>
        <p>chracters for marginal notes?</p>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="act5">
          <div xml:id="act5s1" type="scene" n="1">
            <head>
              <hi rend="italic">Actus Quintus. Scæna Prima.</hi><note type="mansNote" resp="#formerOwner" subtype="beReady">Jamy &amp; Srvant</note>
            </head>
            <stage type="entrance" place="center">Enter Violante and Servant.</stage><note type="mansNote" resp="#formerOwner" subtype="crosshatchedlines">Cross-hatched lines.</note>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Madam hees come.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp><stage type="business" place="right">Chaire and stooles out.</stage>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Tis well how did he looke,</l>
                <l>When he knew from whom you were sent? was he not <lb rend="turnover"/>startled</l>
                <l>Or confident? or fearfull?</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>As appear'd</l>
                <l>Like one that knew his fortune at the worst,</l>
                <l>And car'd not what could follow.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>'Tis the better</l>
                <l>Reach me a Chaire: So bring him in, be carefull</l>
                <l>That none disturb us: I will try his temper,</l>
                <l>And if I find him apt for my employments,</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <stage type="entrance" place="center">Enter Jamy, Servant.</stage><note type="mansNote" resp="#formerOwner" subtype="crosshatchedlines">Cross-hatched lines.</note>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I'll worke him to my ends, if not I shall</l>
                <l>Find other Engines.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Ther's my Ladie,</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Leave us</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Iam.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>You sent for me?</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I did, and do's the favour,</l>
                <l>Your present state considered, and my power,</l>
                <l>Deserve no greater Ceremonie?</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Iam.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Ceremonie?</l>
                <l>I use to pay that, where I doe owe dutie,</l>
                <l>Not to my Brothers wife: I cannot fawne,</l>
                <l>If you expect it from me, you are cozen'd,</l>
                <l>And so farewell.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>He beares up still; I like it,</l>
                <l>Pray you a word</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Iam.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Yes: I will give you hearing</l>
                <l>On equall termes, and sit by you as a friend,</l>
                <l>But not stand as a Sutour: Now your pleasure?</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>You are very bold.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Iam.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>'Tis fitt: since you are proud</l>
                <l>I was not made to feed that foolish humour,</l>
                <l>With flattery and observance</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Yet, with your favour,</l>
                <l>A little forme ioyn'd with respect to her,</l>
                <l>That can add to your wants, or free you from 'em</l>
                <l>(Nay raise you to a fate, beyond your hopes) <stage type="business" place="right">A Table ready co-</stage></l>
                <l>Might well become your wisedome, <stage type="business" place="right">vered with Cloath</stage></l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Iam.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>It would rather <stage type="business" place="right">Napkins Salt</stage></l>
                <l>Write me a Foole, should I but onely think <stage type="business" place="right">Treachers and</stage></l>
                <l>That any good to me, could flow from you, <stage type="business" place="right">Bread.</stage></l>
                <l>Whom for so many yeares: I have found and prov'd</l>
                <l>My greatest Enemy: I am still the same</l>
                <l>My wants have not transform'd me: I dare tell you,</l>
                <l>To your new cerviz'd face, what I have spoken</l>
                <l>Freely behind your back, what I thinke of you,</l>
                <l>You are the proudest thing, and have the least,</l>
                <l>Reason to be so, that I ever read of</l>
                <l>In stature you are a Giantesse: and your Tailour</l>
                <l>Takes measure of you, with a <persName>Iacobs</persName> staffe,</l>
                <l>Or he can never reach you, this is by the way</l>
                <l>For your large size: Now, in a word, or two</l>
                <l>To treat of your Complexion were decorum:</l>
                <l>You are so far from faire, I doubt your Mother</l>
                <l>Was too familliar with the <persName>Moore</persName>, that serv'd her,</l>
                <l>Your Limbes and Features, I passe breifely over,</l>
                <l>As things not worth description; and come roundly</l>
                <l>To your soule, if you have any: for 'tis doubtfull</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I laugh at this, proceed</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Iam.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>This Soule, I speake of</l>
                <l>Or rather salt to keepe this heape of flesh,</l>
                <l>From being a walking stench, like a <placeName>large Inne</placeName>,</l>
                <l>Stands open for the entertainement of</l>
                <l>A!l impious practices: but ther's no Corner</l>
                <l>An honest thought can take up: and as it were not</l>
                <l>Sufficent in your self to comprehend</l>
                <l>All wicked plots, you have taught the Foole, my Brother</l>
                <l>By your contagion, almost to put off</l>
                <l>The nature of the man, and turn'd him <persName>Devill</persName></l>
                <l>Because he should be like you, and I hope</l>
                <l>Will march to hell together: I have spoken,</l>
                <l>Like a tame Asse; and when most spur'd and gall'd</l>
                <l>Were never Master of the Spleene or Spirit,</l>
                <l>That could raise up the anger of a man,</l>
                <l>And force it into action,</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Jamie.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>This Soule, I speake of</l><note resp="#mim" type="lineNumber">60</note>
                <l>Or rather salt to keepe this heape of flesh,</l>
                <l>From being a walking stench, like a <placeName>large Inne</placeName>,</l>
                <l>Stands open for the entertainement of</l>
                <l>A!l impious practices: but ther's no Corner</l>
                <l>An honest thought can take up: and as it were not</l><note resp="#mim" type="lineNumber">65</note>
                <l>Sufficent in your self to comprehend</l>
                <l>All wicked plots, you have taught the Foole, my Brother</l>
                <l>By your contagion, almost to put off</l>
                <l>The nature of the man, and turn'd him <persName>Devill</persName></l>
                <l>Because he should be like you, and I hope</l><note resp="#mim" type="lineNumber">70</note>
                <l>Will march to hell together: I have spoken,</l>
                <l>And if the limming you, in your true Colours</l>
                <l>Can make the Painter gracious, I stand readie</l>
                <l>For my reward, or if my words distaste you</l>
                <l>I weigh it not, for though your Groomes were ready</l>
                <l>To cut my throat for't, be assur'd I cannot</l>
                <l>Use other Language</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Violante.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>You thinke you have said now,</l>
                <l>Like a brave fellow: in this Womans War</l>
                <l>You ever have bin train'd: spoke big, but suffer'd</l>
                <l>Like a tame Asse; and when most spur'd and gall'd</l>
                <l>Were never Master of the Spleene or Spirit,</l>
                <l>That could raise up the anger of man,</l>
                <l>And force it into action,</l><note resp="#mim" type="lineNumber">75</note>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Iam.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Yes vile Creature</l>
                <l>Wer't thou a subject worthy of my Sword,</l>
                <l>Or that thy death, this moment, could call <placeName>home</placeName>,</l>
                <l>My banish'd hopes, thou now wer't dead: dead (woman)</l>
                <l>But being as thou art it is sufficient</l>
                <l>I scorne thee, and contemne thee</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>This shewes nobly:</l>
                <fw type="catch">I</fw>
                <pb n="TSC-022"
                  facs="https://digital.libraries.psu.edu/digital/collection/emblem/id/4402/rec/4"/>
                <fw type="pageNum">46</fw>
                <l>I must confesse it: I am taken with it</l>
                <l>For you had kneeld, and whind and shew'd a base</l>
                <l>And low deiected mind, I had despis'd you</l>
                <l>This Bravery (in your adverse fortune) conquers</l>
                <l>And do's command me, and upon the sudaine</l>
                <l>I feele a kind of pittie, growing in me,</l>
                <l>For your misfortunes, pittie some sayes the Parent,</l>
                <l>Of future love, and I repent my part,</l>
                <l>So far in what you have suffered, that I could,</l>
                <l>(But you are cold) doe something to repaire</l>
                <l>What your base Brother (such <persName>Iami</persName> I thinke him)</l>
                <l>Hath brought to ruine</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Iam.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Ha?</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Be not amaz'd,</l>
                <l>Our injuries are equall in his Bastard</l>
                <l>You are familliar with what I grone for</l>
                <l>And though the name of Husband holds a tye</l>
                <l>Beyond a Brother, I, a poore weake Woman,</l>
                <l>Am sensible, and tender of a wrong,</l>
                <l>And to revenge it, would break through all letts,</l>
                <l>That durst oppose me.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Iam.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Is it possible?</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>By this kisse: start not: thus much, as a stranger</l>
                <l>You may take from me; But, if you were pleas'd,</l>
                <l>I should select you, as a bosome Friend,</l>
                <l>I would print 'em, thus, and, thus,</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Iam.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Keepe off.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Come neare,</l>
                <l>Neere into the Cabinet of my Counsailes:</l>
                <l>Simplicity and patience dwells with Fooles,</l>
                <l>And let them beare those burthens, which wise men</l>
                <l>Boldly shake off; Be mine and ioyne with me,</l>
                <l>And when that I have rais'd you to a fortune,</l>
                <l>(Doe not deny your selfe the happie meanes)</l>
                <l>You'l looke on me, with more iudicious eies</l>
                <l>And sweare I am most faire,</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Iam.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>What would this Woman?</l>
                <l>The purpose of these words? speake not in ridles</l>
                <l>And when I understand, what you would counsell,</l>
                <l>My answer shall be suddaine,</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Thus then <persName>Iami</persName>,</l>
                <l>The objects of our fury, are they same,</l>
                <l>For young <persName>Ascanio</persName>, whom you snake like hug'd</l>
                <l>(Frozen with wants to death) in your warme bosome,</l>
                <l>Lives to supplant you in your certaine hopes,</l>
                <l>And kills in me all comfort.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Iam.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Now 'tis plaine,</l>
                <l>I apprehend you: and were he remov'd—</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>You, once againe, were the undoubted heire.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Iam.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>'Tis not to be denyed; I was ice before,</l>
                <l>But now ye have fir'd me,—</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I'l add fuell to it,</l>
                <l>And by a nearer cut, doe you but steere</l>
                <l>As I direct you bring our Bark into</l>
                <l>The <placeName>Port</placeName> of happines,</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Iam.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>How?</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>By <persName>Henriques</persName> death:</l>
                <l>But you'll say hee's your Brother; in great fortunes</l>
                <l>(Which are epitomes of <placeName>States &amp; Kingdomes</placeName>) <stage type="business" place="right">Dishes cove-</stage></l>
                <l>The politicke brooke no Rivalls. <stage type="business" place="right">red with pa-</stage></l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Iam.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Excellent. <stage type="business" place="right">pers in each</stage></l>
                <l>For sure I thinke out of a scrupulous feare, <stage type="business" place="right">ready.</stage></l>
                <l>To feed in expectation, when I may</l>
                <l>(Dispensing but a little with my conscience)</l>
                <l>Come into full possession, would not argue</l>
                <l>One that desir'd to thrive,</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Now you speake like</l>
                <l>A man that knowes the <placeName>World</placeName>.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Jam.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I needs must learne</l>
                <l>That have so good a Tutresse: And what thinke you,</l>
                <l>(<persName><roleName>Don</roleName> Henrique</persName> and <persName>Ascanio</persName> cut off)</l>
                <l>That none may live, that shall desire to trace us</l>
                <l>In our black pathes, if that <persName>Octavio</persName></l>
                <l>His foster Father' and the sad <persName>Jacinta</persName>,</l>
                <l>(Faith pittie her, and free her from her Sorrowes)</l>
                <l>Should fall Companions with 'em? When we are red</l>
                <l>With murther, let us often bath in blood,</l>
                <l>The collour will be scarlet.</l>
              </lg>  
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>And that's glorious,</l><note type="mansNote" resp="formerOwner" subtype="beReady">be ready</note>
                <l>And will protect the fact</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Jam.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Suppose this don:</l>
                <l>(If undiscovered,) we may get for money,</l>
                <l>(As that you know buyes any thing in <placeName>Rome</placeName>)</l>
                <l>A dispensation</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>And be married?</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Jam.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>True.</l>
                <l>Or if it be knowne, trusse up our Gold and Jewells,</l>
                <l>And fly to some <placeName>free State</placeName>, and there with scorne—</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Laugh at the lawes of <placeName>Spaine</placeName>.</l>
                <l>'Twere admirable.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Iam.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>We shall beget rare Children. I am rap'd with</l>
                <l>The meere imagination—</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Shall it be don?</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Iam.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Shall? tis too tedious: furnish me with meanes</l>
                <l>To hire the instruments, and to your self,</l>
                <l>Say it is done already: I will shew you,</l>
                <l>'Ere the Sun set, how much you have wrought upon me,</l>
                <l>Your province is onely to use some meanes,</l>
                <l>To send my Brother, to the Grove that's neighbour,</l>
                <l>To the <placeName>west Port of th' Citie</placeName>; leave the rest,</l>
                <l>To my owne practice; I have talk'd too long.</l>
                <l>But now will doe: this kisse, with my Confession,</l>
                <l>To worke a fell revenge: A mans a foole,</l>
                <l>If not instructed in a <placeName>Womans Schoole</placeName>.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <stage type="exit" place="right">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div xml:id="act5s2" type="scene" n="2">
            <head>
              <hi rend="italic">Scæna Secunda.</hi><note type="mansNote" resp="#formerOwner" subtype="crosshatchedlines">Cross-hatched lines.</note>
            </head>
            <stage type="entrance" place="center">Enter Bartolus Algazier and a Paratour.</stage><note type="mansNote" resp="#formerOwner" subtype="beReady">Mill be ready</note>
            <stage type="business" place="center">The Table set out and stooles.</stage>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>You are well enough disguiz'd, furnish the Table,</l>
                <l>Make no shew, what ye are, till I discover</l>
                <l>Not a soule knowes ye here: be quick and dilligent,</l>
                <l>These youthes, I have invited to a Breakfast,</l>
                <l>But what the Sawce will be, I am of opinion</l>
                <l>I shall take off the edges of their Appetites,</l>
                <l>And greaze their gums, for eating hartily;</l>
                <l>This month of two they have plaid their prizes with me</l>
                <l>And their severall flurts they have lighted dange-</l>
                <l>But sure I shall be quit: I heare ߴem comming  (rously</l>
                <l>Goe off, and wait the bringing in your service,</l>
                <l>And doe it handsomely: you know where to have it</l>
                <stage type="entrance" place="center">Enter Millanes, Arsenio, Lopez, Diego.</stage>
                <l>Wellcome i'Faith,</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Ars.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>That's well said, honest Lawyer,</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lop.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Said like a Neighbour</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Wellcome all: all over</l>
                <l>And let's be merry:</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Mil.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>To that end we came Sir,</l>
                <l>An hower of freedome's worth an age of juglings,</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Die.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I am come too Sir, to specifie my Stomach</l>
                <l>A poore reteyner to your worships bountie,</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <fw type="catch" rend="italic">Bar.</fw>
            <pb n="TSC-023"
              facs="https://digital.libraries.psu.edu/digital/collection/emblem/id/4403/rec/4"/>
            <fw type="pageNum">47</fw>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>And thou shalt have it fill'd, my merry <persName>Diego</persName>,</l>
                <l>My liberall, and my bonney bounteous <persName>Diego</persName></l>
                <l>Even filld till it groane againe</l><note type="mansNote" resp="#formerOwner" subtype="beReady">Ama: lean: be ready.</note>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Di.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Let it have faire play,</l>
                <l>And if it founder then—</l>
                <l>I'll tell ye neighbours,</l>
                <l>Though I were angry yesterday, with ye all,</l>
                <l>And very angry for thought ye bobd me.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lop.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>No, no, by no meanes.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>No, when I considered</l>
                <l>It was a jest, and carried off so quaintly</l>
                <l>It made me merry: very merry, Gentlemen,</l>
                <l>I doe confes I could not sleepe to thinke on't</l>
                <l>The mirth so tickled me, I could not slumber,</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lop.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Good mirth do's worke so: honest mirth,</l>
                <l>Now, should we have meant in earnest—</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>You say true Neighbour,</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lop.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>It might bred such a distant and sowrenesse,</l>
                <l>Such fond imaginations in your Braines, Sir</l>
                <l>For things trust home in earnest—</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Very certaine</l>
                <l>But I know ye all for merry waggs, and ere long</l>
                <l>You shall know me too. in another fashion</l>
                <l>Though y'are pamper'd ye shall beare part ߴoth burthen.</l>
                <stage type="entrance" place="center">Enter Amaranta and Leandro.</stage><note type="mansNote" resp="#formerOwner" subtype="crosshatchedlines">Cross-hatched lines.</note>
                <l>Come Wife; Come bid 'em wellcome; Come my Jewell:</l>
                <l>And Pupill, you shall come too; nere hand backward,</l>
                <l>Come, come the womans pleas'd, her angers over,</l>
                <l>Come, be not bashfull,</l><note type="mansNote" resp="#formerOwner" subtype="other">Algazers with dishes ready</note>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Am.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>What do's he prepare here?</l>
                <l>Sure ther's no meate 'ith house at least none drest,</l>
                <l>Do's he meane to mock 'em? or some new bred Crotchet</l>
                <l>Come o're his braines; I doe not like his kindnes?</l>
                <l>But silence best becomes me: if he meane foule play</l>
                <l>Sure they are enough to right themselves and let 'em,</l>
                <l>I'll sit by, so they beat him not to powder,</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l rend="right">(Neighbour</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Bring in the meate there, ha? Sit downe deare</l>
                <l>A little meate needs little Complement,</l>
                <l>Sit downe I say:</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Am.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>What doe you meane by this Sir?</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Convay away their weapons handsomely,</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Am.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>You know ther's none ith' house to answer ye,</l>
                <l>But the poore Girle; you know ther's no meat neither</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Peace and be quiet; I shall make you smoak els</l>
                <l>Ther's men aud Meate enough, set it downe formally</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <stage type="entrance" place="center">Enter Algazeirs with dishes.</stage><note type="mansNote" resp="#formerOwner" subtype="crosshatchedlines">Cross-hatched lines.</note>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Am.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I feare some lew'd tricke, yet I dare not speake on't</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I have no dainties for ye Gentlemen,</l>
                <l>Nor lodes of meat, to make the roome smell of'em</l>
                <l>Onely a dish to every man I have dedicated,</l>
                <l>And if I have pleas'd his appetite,</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lop.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>O, a Capon,</l>
                <l>A Bird of grace, and by thy will, I honour it</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Di.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>For me some fortie pound of lovely Beeffe,</l>
                <l>Plac'd in a <placeName>mediterranean sea of Brewisse</placeName></l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Fall to fall to that we may drinke and laugh after</l>
                <l>Wait diligently knaves,</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Mil.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>What rare bits this?</l>
                <l>An execution, blesse me!</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Nay take it to ye</l>
                <l>Ther's no avoiding it 'tis somewhat tough Sir,</l>
                <l>But a good stomach will endure it easely</l>
                <l>The sum is, but a thousand duckets Sir,</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Ars.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>A Capias from my Surgeon, and my Silke man,</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Your carefull makers but they have mard your diet</l>
                <l>Stir not, your Swords are gon: ther's no avoiding me</l>
                <l>And these are <persName>Algazeirs</persName>, doe you heare that passing bell?</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lop.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>A strong Citation, blesse me!</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Out with your Beads, Curat</l>
                <l>The devills in your dish: bell, booke, and Candell,</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Diego.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>A warrant to appeare before the Judges?</l><note resp="#mim" type="lineNumber">90</note>
                <l>I must needs rise, and turne to'th wall.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Ye need not,</l>
                <l>Your feare I hope will make ye find your Breeches,</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>All.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>We are betraid</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Invited, doe not wrong me,</l>
                <l>Fall to, good Guests, you have dilligent men about ye,</l>
                <l>Ye shall want nothing, that may persecute ye</l>
                <l>These will not see ye start; Have I now found ye</l>
                <l>Have I requited ye? You fool d the Lawyer,</l>
                <l>And thought it meritorious, to abuse him,</l>
                <l>A thick ram headed knave: you rid you spurd him,</l>
                <l>And glorified your witts, the more ye wrongd him;</l>
                <l>Within this hower, ye shall have all your Creditours,</l>
                <l>A second dish of new debts, come upon ye</l>
                <l>And new invitements to the whip (<persName><roleName>Don</roleName> Diego</persName>)</l>
                <l>And Excommunications for the Learned Curat,</l>
                <l>A Masque of all your furies shall dance to ye,</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Ars.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>You dare not use us thus?</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>You shall be bobd ( Gentlemen)</l>
                <l>Stir, and as I have a life, ye goe to <placeName>prison</placeName></l>
                <l>To <placeName>prison</placeName>, without pittie instantly</l>
                <l>Before ye speake another word to <placeName>prison</placeName>.</l>
                <l>I have a better Guard, without, that waytes;</l>
                <l>Doe you see this man, <persName>Don Curat</persName>? 'tis a Paratour</l>
                <l>That comes to tell ye a delightfull story.</l>
                <l>Of an old whore, ye have and then to teach ye</l>
                <l>What is the penaltie; Laugh at me now Sir,</l>
                <l>What Legacie would ye bequeath me now,</l>
                <l>(And pay it on the naile?) to fly my fury?</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lop.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>O gentle Sir,</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Do'st thou hope I will be gentle,</l>
                <l>Thou foolish unconsiderate Curat?</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lop.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Let me goe Sir,</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I'll see thee hang first,</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lop.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>And as I am a true Vicar,</l>
                <l>Hark in your eare hark softly—</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>No, no bribery.</l>
                <l>I'll have my swindge upon thee; Sirha? Rascall?</l>
                <l>You lenten Chaps, you that lay sick, and mockt me,</l>
                <l>Mockt me abhominably; abused me lewdly</l>
                <l>I'll make thee sick at heart, before I leave thee,</l>
                <l>And groane, and dye indeed, and be worth nothing</l>
                <l>Not worth a blessing, nor a Bell to knell for thee,</l>
                <l>A sheete to cover thee, but that thou stealest,</l>
                <l>Stealest from the Merchant, and the Ring he was buried <lb rend="turnover"/>with</l>
                <l>Stealest from his <placeName>Grave</placeName>, doe you smell me now?</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Die.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Have mercy on me!</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>No Psalme of mercy shall hold me from hanging <lb rend="turnunder"/>thee</l>
                <l>How do ye like your Breakfast? 'tis but short, Gentlemen</l>
                <l>But sweet and healthfull; Your punishment and your, Sir</l>
                <l>For some neare reasons, that concerns my Credit,</l>
                <l>I will take to my self.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Am.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Doe Sir, and spare not</l>
                <l>I have bin too good a wife, and too obedient,</l>
                <l>But since ye dare provoke me to be foolish—</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lea.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>She has, yes, and too worthie of your usage,</l>
                <l>Before the world, I justifie her goodnes,</l>
                <l>And turne that man, that dares but taint her vertues,</l>
                <l>To my Swords point; that lying man, that base man,</l>
                <l>Turne him, but face to face, that I may know him</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>What have I here?</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <fw type="catch" rend="italic">Lea.</fw>
            <pb n="TSC-024"
              facs="https://digital.libraries.psu.edu/digital/collection/emblem/id/4404/rec/4"/>
            <fw type="pageNum">48</fw>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lea.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>A Gentleman, a free man,</l>
                <l>One that made triall of this Ladies constancie,</l>
                <l>And found it strong as fate; Leave off your fooling,</l>
                <l>For it you follow this course, you will be Chronicled</l>
                <stage type="entrance" place="center">Enter Iamy and Assistant.</stage>
                <l>For a devill, whilst a Saint she is mentioned,</l>
                <l>Yo know my name indeed; I am now no Lawyer.</l>
                <l>Some comfort now, I hope, or els would I wer hanged up</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Die.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>And yet the Judge, he makes me swet.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>What newes now?</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Iam.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I will justifie upon my life, and Credit</l>
                <l>What you have heard, for truth, and will make proofee of</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Assist.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I will be ready at the appointed hower there,</l>
                <l>And so I leave ye.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Stay I beseech your worship,</l>
                <l>And doe but heare me,</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Iam.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Good Sir, intend this busines,</l>
                <l>And let this bawling Foole; No more words Lawyer,</l>
                <l>And no more angers for I guesse your reasons,</l>
                <l>This Gentleman, i'l justifie in all places,</l>
                <l>And that faire Ladies worth; Let who dare crosse it,</l>
                <l>The Plot was cast by me, to make thee jealous,</l>
                <l>But not to wrong your wife, she is faire and vertous,</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Die.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Take us to mercy too, we beseech your honour,</l>
                <l>[...] shall be justified the way of all flesh els,</l>
                <l>[...]. No more talke nor no more dissention Lawyer,</l>
                <l>[...]w your anger, 'tis a vaine and slight one,</l>
                <l>[...]ou doe; i'll lay your whole life open</l>
                <l>[...]hat all the <placeName>world</placeName> shall i'll bring witnes,</l>
                <l>[...]p before a Judge the ulcerous villanies</l>
                <l>[...]know I know ye, and I can bring witnes.</l>
                <l>[...]. Nay good Sir, noble Sir.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>[...m]</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Be at peace then presently,</l>
                <l>[...]diately take honest and faire truce</l>
                <l>[...] your good Wife and shake hands with that Gen<lb rend="turnover"/>tleman;</l>
                <l>[...]honour'd ye too much, and doe it cheerefully,</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lop.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Take us along, for <placeName>heaven</placeName> sake too.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I am Friends,</l><note type="mansNote" resp="#formerOwner" subtype="beReady">octa: Ja: ascanio be ready</note>
                <l>[...]here is no remedie, I must put up all,</l>
                <l>And like my neighbours rub it ou't by'th shoulders;</l>
                <l>And perfect friends; <persName>Leandro</persName> now I thanke ye,</l>
                <l>And ther's my hand, I have no more grudge to ye,</l>
                <l>But I am too meane henceforward for your Companie,</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lea.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I shall not trouble ye,</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Ars.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>We will be friends too:</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Mil.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Nay Lawyer, you shall not fright us farther,</l>
                <l>For all your <persName>devills</persName> wee will bolt,</l>
              </lg>  
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I grant ye.</l>
                <l>The Gentlemans your Baile, and thank him comming,</l>
                <l>Did not he know me too well, you should smart for't;</l>
                <l>Goe all in peace, but when ye Foole next, Gentlemen,</l>
                <l>Come not to me to Breakfast.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Die.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I'l be bak'd first.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>And pray ye remember, when ye are bold &amp; merry,</l>
                <l>The Lawyers Bancket, and the Sawce he gave ye,</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Iam.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Come: goe along; I have employment for ye,</l>
                <l>Employment for your lewd braynes too, to coole ye.</l>
                <l>For all, for every one.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>All.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>We are all your Servants.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Die.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>All, all for any thing, from this day forward,</l>
                <l>I'l hate all Breakefasts, and depend on dinners</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Iam.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I am glad you come off faire</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lea.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>The faire has blest me.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <stage type="exit" place="right">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div xml:id="act5s3" type="scene" n="3">
            <head>
              <hi rend="italic">Scena Tertia.</hi>
            </head>
            <stage type="entrance" place="center">Enter Octavio, Iacinta, Ascanio.</stage><note type="mansNote" resp="#formerOwner" subtype="crosshatchedlines">Cross-hatched lines.</note>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>This is the place, but why are appointed</l>
                <l>By <persName><roleName>Don</roleName> Jami</persName> to stay here, is a depth</l><note type="mansNote" resp="#formerOwner" subtype="beReady">Henry &amp; Jami be ready</note>
                <l>I cannot sound,</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Asc.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Beleev't he is too noble,</l>
                <l>To purpose any thing but for our good</l>
                <l>Had I assurance of a thousand Lives,</l>
                <l>And with them perpetuitie of pleasures,</l>
                <l>And should loose all, if he prov'd only false,</l>
                <l>Yet I durst run the hazard,</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Iac.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>'Tis our comfort,</l>
                <l>We cannot be more wretched then we are,</l>
                <l>And death concludes all misery,</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Undiscovered</l>
                <stage type="entrance" place="center">Enter Henrique, Iami.</stage><note type="mansNote" resp="#formerOwner" subtype="crosshatchedlines">Cross-hatched lines.</note>
                <l>We must attend him</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Asc.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Our stay is not long</l>
                <l>With him <persName><roleName>Don</roleName> Henrique</persName>?</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Iac.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Now I feare;</l>
                <l>Be silent.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Hen.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Why do'st thou follow me?</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Iam.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>To save your life,</l>
                <l>A plot is laid for't, all my wrongs forgot,</l>
                <l>I have a Brothers Love.</l><note type="mansNote" resp="#formerOwner" subtype="beReady">Le: Mill: ar: bar be ready</note>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Hen.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>But thy false self,</l>
                <l>I feare no enemy.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Iam.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>You have no Friend,</l>
                <l>But what breathes in me: If you move a step</l>
                <l>Beyond this ground you tread on: you are lost.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Hen.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>'Tis by thy practice then: I am sent hither</l>
                <l>To meete her, that prefers my life, and safetie</l>
                <l>Before her owne.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Iam.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>That you should be abus'd'thus</l>
                <l>With weake credulitie: She for whose sake,</l>
                <l>You have forgot we had one noble Father,</l>
                <l>Or that one Mother bare us, for whose love,</l>
                <l>You breake a contract, to which <placeName>heaven</placeName> was witnes,</l>
                <l>To satisfie whose pride, and willfull humour,</l>
                <l>You have expos'd a sweet, and hopefull Son,</l>
                <l>To all the miseries, that want can bring him,</l>
                <l>And such a Son, though you are the most obdurate,</l>
                <l>To give whom entertainement Savages</l>
                <l>Would quit their Caves themselves, to keepe him from</l>
                <l>Bleake cold, and hunger: This dissembling Woman,</l>
                <l>This Idoll, whom you worship: all your love</l>
                <l>And service trod under her feete, designes you</l>
                <l>To fill a <placeName>grave</placeName> or dead to lye a pray,</l>
                <l>For Wolves, and vultures.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Hen.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>'Tis false; I defie thee,</l>
                <l>And stand upon my Guard</l><note type="mansNote" resp="#formerOwner" subtype="crosshatchedlines">Cross-hatched lines.</note>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <stage type="entrance" place="center">Enter Leandro Millanes, Arsenio, Bart. Lopez, Diego, Octavio Iacinta Ascanio and Servants.</stage>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Iam.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Alas, 'tis weake:</l>
                <l>Come on since you will teach me to be cruell,</l>
                <l>By having no faith, in me, take your fortune,</l>
                <l>Bring the rest forth, and bind them fast.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>My Lord.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Asc.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>In what have we offended?</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <fw type="catch" rend="italic">Iam.</fw>
            <pb n="TSC-025"
              facs="https://digital.libraries.psu.edu/digital/collection/emblem/id/4405/rec/4"/>
            <fw type="sig">H</fw>
            <fw type="pageNum">49</fw>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Iam.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I am deafe,</l>
                <l>And following my will, I doe not stand</l><note type="mansNote" subtype="beReady">Violante be ready</note>
                <l>Accomptable to reason: See her Ring</l>
                <l>(The first pledge of your love, and service to her)</l>
                <l>Delivered as a Warrant for your death:</l>
                <l>These Bags of gold you gave up to her trust,</l>
                <l>(The use of which, you did deny your selfe)</l>
                <l>Bestow'd on me, and with a prodigal! hand,</l>
                <l>Whom she pick'd forth to be the Architect</l>
                <l>Of her most bloudy building; and to See</l>
                <l>These Instruments, to bring Materials</l>
                <l>To raise it up, she bad me spare no cost,</l>
                <l>And (as a surplusage) offer'd her selfe</l>
                <l>To be at my devotion.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Henr.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>O accurs'd!</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Iam.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>But be incredulous still; think this my plot;</l>
                <l>Fashion excuses to your selfe, and sweare</l>
                <l>That she is innocent, that she doats on ye;</l>
                <l>Believe this, as a fearefull Dreame, and that</l>
                <l>You lie not at my mercy, which in this</l>
                <l>I will shew onely: She her selfe shall give</l>
                <l>The dreadfull Sentence, to remove all scruple</l>
                <l>Who 'tis that sends you to the <placeName>other world</placeName>.</l>
                <stage type="entrance" place="center">Enter Violante.</stage><note type="mansNote" resp="#formerOwner" subtype="crosshatchedlines">Cross-hatched lines.</note><note type="mansNote" resp="#formerOwner" subtype="beReady">assistant 7amp: officers be ready</note>
                <l>Appeares my <persName>Violante</persName>? speake (my dearest)</l>
                <l>Do's not the object please you?</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>More then if</l>
                <l>All Treasure that's above the <placeName>earth</placeName>, with that,</l>
                <l>That lyes conceal'd in both the <placeName>Indian Mines</placeName>,</l>
                <l>Were laid downe at my feet: O bold <persName>Iamy</persName></l>
                <l>Thou onely canst deserve me.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Iam,</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I am forward,</l>
                <l>And (as you easily may perceive,) I sleepe not</l>
                <l>On your commands.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <stage type="entrance" place="center">Enter Assistant and Officers.</stage><note type="mansNote" resp="#formerOwner" subtype="crosshatchedlines">Cross-hatched lines.</note>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>But yet they live: I look'd</l>
                <l>To find them dead.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Iam.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>That was defer'd, that you</l>
                <l>Might triumph in their misery, and have the powre</l>
                <l>To say they are not,</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>'Twas well thought upon:</l>
                <l>This kisse, and all the pleasures of my Bed</l>
                <l>This night, shall thank thee.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Hen.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Monster!</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>You Sir, that</l>
                <l>Would have me mother Bastards, being unable</l>
                <l>To honour me with one Child of mine owne,</l>
                <l>That underneath my Roofe, kept your cast-Strumpet,</l>
                <l>And out of my Revenues, would maintaine</l>
                <l>Her riotous issue: Now you find what 'tis</l>
                <l>To tempt a woman: with as little feeling</l>
                <l>As I turne off a slave, that is unfit</l>
                <l>To doe me service; of a horse, or dog</l>
                <l>That have out-liv'd their use, I shake thee off,</l>
                <l>To make thy peace with <placeName>heaven</placeName>.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Hen.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I doe deserve this,</l>
                <l>And never truly felt before, what sorrow</l>
                <l>Attends on willfull dotage.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>For you, Misstris,</l>
                <l>That had the pleasure of his youth before me,</l>
                <l>And triumph'd in the fruit, that you had by him,</l>
                <l>But that I thinke, to have the Bastard strangled</l>
                <l>Before thy face, and thou with speed to follow</l>
                <l>The way he leades thee, is sufficent torture,</l>
                <l>I would cut off thy nose, put out thine eyes,</l>
                <l>And set my foot on these bewitching lips,</l>
                <l>That had the start of mine: but as thou art,</l>
                <l>Goe to the <placeName>grave</placeName> unpittied.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Assist.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Who would beleeve</l>
                <l>Such rage could be in woman?</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Viol,</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>For this Fellow,</l>
                <l>He is not worth my knowledge.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Iam.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Let him live then,</l>
                <l>Since you esteeme him innocent.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>No, <persName>Jamy</persName>,</l>
                <l>He shall make up the messe: now strike together</l>
                <l>And let them fall so.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Assist.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Unheard of crueltie!</l>
                <l>I can endure no longer: seize on her.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Am I betrai'd?</l>
                <l>Is this thy faith, <persName>Iamy</persName>?</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Iam.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Could your desires</l>
                <l>Challenge performance of a deed so horrid?</l>
                <l>Or, though that you had sold your selfe to hell,</l>
                <l>I should make up the bargaine? Live (deare Brother)</l>
                <l>Live long, and happy: I forgive you freely;</l>
                <l>To have done you this serviee, is to me</l>
                <l>A faire Inheritance: And how e're harsh language</l>
                <l>(Call'd on, by your rough usage) pass'd my lipps,</l>
                <l>In my heart, I ever lov'd you: All my labours</l>
                <l>Were but to shew, how much your love was cozen'd,</l>
                <l>When it beheld it selfe in this false Glasse,</l>
                <l>That did abuse you; and I am so far</l>
                <l>From envying young <persName>Ascanio</persName> his good fortune,</l>
                <l>That if your State were mine, I would adopt him.</l>
                <l>These are the Murtherers, my noble Friends,</l>
                <l>Which (to make triall of her bloudy purpose)</l>
                <l>I won, to come disguis'd thus.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Hen.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I am too full</l>
                <l>Of griefe, and shame to speake: but what I'le doe,</l>
                <l>Shall to the world proclaime my penitence;</l>
                <l>And howsoever I have liv'd, I'le die</l>
                <l>A much chang'd man.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Iam.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Were it but possible</l>
                <l>You could make satisfaction to this woman,</l>
                <l>Our joyes were perfect.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Hen.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>That's my onely comfort,</l>
                <l>That it is in my power: I ne're was married</l>
                <l>To this bad woman, though I doted on her,</l>
                <l>But daily did deferre it, still expecting</l>
                <l>When griefe would kill <persName>Jacintha</persName>.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Assist.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>All is come out,</l>
                <l>And finds a faire successe: take her <persName><roleName>Don</roleName> Henrique</persName>,</l>
                <l>And once againe embrace your Son.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Hen.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Most gladly.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Assist.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Your Brother hath deserv'd well.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Hen.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>And shall share</l>
                <l>The moitie of my State,</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Assist.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I have heart, Advocate,</l>
                <l>What an ill Instrument you have bin to him,</l>
                <l>For this time strengthen him, with honest counsells,</l>
                <l>As you'le deserve my pardon.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I'le change my Copy:</l>
                <l>But I am punish'd, for I feare I have had</l>
                <l>A smart blow, though unseene.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Assist.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l> Curat, and Sexton,</l>
                <l>I have heard of you too, let me heare no more,</l>
                <l>And what's past, is forgotten; For this woman,</l>
                <l>Though her intent were bloody, yet our Law</l>
                <l>Calls it not death: yet that her punishment</l>
                <fw type="catch" >May</fw>
                <pb n="TSC-026"
                  facs="https://digital.libraries.psu.edu/digital/collection/emblem/id/4406/rec/4"/>
                <fw type="pageNum">50</fw>
                <l>May deter others from such bad attempts,</l>
                <l>The Dowry she brought with her shall be emploi'd</l>
                <l>To build a <placeName>Nunnery</placeName>, where she shall spend</l>
                <l>The remnant of her life.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Since I have miss'd my ends,</l>
                <l>I scorne what can fall on me.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Assist.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>The strict discipline</l>
                <l>Of the Church, will teach you better thoughts. and Sig<lb rend="turnunder"/>niors,-</l>
                <l>You that are Batchelours, if you ever marry,</l>
                <l>In <persName>Bartolus</persName>, you may behold the issue</l>
                <l>Of Covetousnesse, and Jealousie; And of dotage,</l>
                <l>and falshood in, <persName><roleName>Don</roleName> Henrique</persName>, keep a meane then;</l>
                <l rend="italic">For be assur'd that weake man meets all ill,</l>
                <l rend="italic">That gives himselfe up to a womans will.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <stage type="exit" place="right">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
      </div>
         <div xml:id="prologue" type="front" n="1" rend="italic"><!-- help with prologue formatting and who is speaking -->
            <l><hi rend="roman">T</hi>O tell ye (Gentlemen,) we have a Play,</l>
            <l>A new one too, and that 'tis launch'd to day,</l>
            <l>The Name ye know, that's nothing to my Story;</l>
            <l>To tell ye, 'tis familiar, uoid of Glory;</l>
            <l>Of <placeName>State</placeName>, of Bitternesse: of wit you'll say,</l>
            <l>For that is now held wit, that tends that way,</l>
            <l>Which we avoid: To tell ye to 'tis merry,</l>
            <l>And meant to make ye pleasant, and not weary:</l>
            <l><hi rend="roman">T</hi>he <placeName>Streame</placeName> that guides ye, easie to attend:</l>
            <l>To tell ye that 'tis good, is to no end,</l>
            <l>If you believe not. Nay, to goe thus far,</l>
            <l><hi rend="roman">T</hi>o sweare it, if you sweare against, is war</l>
            <l><hi rend="roman">T</hi>o assure you anything, unlesse you see,</l>
            <l>And so conceive, is vanity in me;</l>
            <l>Therefore I leave it to it selfe, and pray</l>
            <l>Like a good Barke, it may worke out to day,</l>
            <l>And stem all doubts; 'twas built for such a proofe,</l>
            <l>And we hope high ly: if she lye aloofe</l>
            <l>For her owne vantage, to give wind at will,</l>
            <l>Why let her worke, onely be you still,</l>
            <l>And sweet opinion'd, and we are bound to say,</l>
            <l>You are worthy Judges, and you crowne the Play.</l>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="epilogue" type="back" n="1">
            <head>Epilogue.</head>
            <sp>
               <l>T<hi rend="italic">He Play is done, yet our suit never ends,</hi></l>
               <l>Still when you part, you would stil part our friends,</l>
               <l>Our noblest friends; if ought have falne amis,</l>
               <l>O let it be sufficient, that it is,</l>
               <l>And you have pardon'd it. In Buildings great</l>
               <l>All the whole Body, cannot be so neat,</l>
               <l>But something may be mended; Those are faire,</l>
               <l>And worthy love, that may destroy, but spare.</l>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="finis" type="back" n="1">
            <head rend="italic">F I N I S.</head>
         </div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
