<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="TSC">THE SPANISH CURATE</title>
            <author>John Fletcher</author>
            <author>Philip Massinger</author>
	<respStmt>
          <resp>Edited and encoded by:</resp>
          <name xml:id="mim">Maria Isabel Maza</name>
        </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Published by the Open Publishing Unit of The Pennsylvania State University Libraries.</publisher>
            <availability>
               <p>Attribution 4.0 International (CC BY 4.0)</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>The Digital Beaumont &amp; Fletcher (1647) Project</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor:</resp>
               <name xml:id="cmlb">Claire M.L. Bourne</name>
            </respStmt> 
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Project Manager:</resp>
               <name xml:id="hf">Heather Froehlich</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Text Encoding Consultant:</resp>
               <name xml:id="jr">John Russell</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Open Publishing Program Coordinator</resp>
               <name>Ally Laird</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Open Access Systems Developer</resp>
               <name xml:id="ag">Andrew Gearhart</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Annotator(s)</resp>
               <name xml:id="formerOwner">Former Owner - Author of Manuscript Annotations</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Graduate Assistants:</resp>
               <name>Taylor Hare</name>
               <name>David LeBlanc</name>
               <name>Danielle Ryle</name>
               <name>Lauren Cenci</name>
               <name>Maria Isabel Maza</name>
            </respStmt>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Francis Beaumont</author>
                  <author>John Fletcher</author>
                  <title>Comedies and Tragedies Written by Francis Beavmont and Iohn Fletcher,
                     Gentlemen. Never printed before, And now published by the Authours
                     Originall Copies.</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>Humprey Robinson</publisher>
                     <publisher>the three Pidgeons</publisher>
                     <publisher>Humphrey Moseley</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>The Prince Armes in St. Pauls Church-yard</pubPlace>
                     <date>1647</date>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier xml:id="psf">
                  <country>The United States</country>
                  <region>Pennsylvania</region>
                  <institution>Pennsylvania State University</institution>
                  <repository>Eberly Family Special Collections Library</repository>
                  <collection>Emblem Books</collection>
                  <msName>COMEDIES AND TRAGEDIES</msName> 
                  <msName>  
                     <rs>
                        3083972 
                     </rs>
                  </msName>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p>This document is a simplified "true-to-text" XML version of <title rend="italic">The Spanish Curate</title> based on Pennsylvania State University's annotated copy of the 1647
            Beaumont &amp; Fletcher first folio. Major textual elements and attributes have been captured based on how they appear in the folio. Whenever possible, editorial
            interventions have been minimalized or avoided entirely. This document is meant to serve as a pedagogical tool by which students of Early Modern literature can learn
            to construct edited XML versions of the play.</p>        
         <projectDesc>
            <p>
               The Digital Beaumont &amp; Fletcher (1647) is a collaborative editorial project aimed at making many of the rarely edited—and, as a result, rarely taught—plays in the
               “Beaumont &amp; Fletcher” canon accessible to student readers and freely available online for classroom use. This project was inspired by the distinctive copy of Comedies
               and Tragedies Written by Francis Beavmont And Iohn Fletcher Gentlemen (1647) held by Penn State University’s Eberly Family Special Collections Library. In addition to
               preserving evidence of ownership dating to as early as 1703, Penn State’s copy of this printed play collection also includes three plays with handwritten marginalia,
               suggesting that the book might have been used to facilitate performance in the late seventeenth century. This project is also motivated by a desire to make the texts and
               other features of this book more widely known and readable. As a first step, the whole volume has now been fully digitized, thanks to the department of Preservation,
               Conservation, and Digitization at Penn State Libraries.
            </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Provides details of editorial principles and practices applied during the encoding of a text</p>
            <normalization source="OED">
               <p>ALL words converted to Modern British spelling 
                  following Oxford English Dictionary.</p>
            </normalization>
            <punctuation>
               <p>Punctuation was modernized to register full syntactical units.</p>
            </punctuation>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <handNotes>
            <handNote>
               <p>
                  This edition of The Spanish Curate contains the marginal notes found in the Penn State Libraries' copy of the 1647 folio. These manuscript notes are particually attentive to
                  the performance of the play, and prepare actors for entrances and emphasize stage directions throughout the text. These manuscript notes have been added to the text without modernization
                  spelling of puncuation.
               </p>
            </handNote>
         </handNotes>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
       <div xml:id="act1" type="act" n="1">
        <fw type="sig">E</fw>
        <pb n="TSC-001"
          facs="https://digital.libraries.psu.edu/digital/collection/emblem/id/4381/rec/4"/>
        <fw type="pageNum">25</fw>
        <head>
          <title>THE SPANISH CURAT</title>
        </head>
          <div xml:id="act1s1" type="scene" n="1">
            <head>
              <hi rend="italic">Actus Primus. Scaena Prima.</hi>
            </head>
            <stage type="entrance" place="center">Enter Angelo, Milanes, Arsenio.</stage>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Arsenio.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l><persName><hi rend="ornInit">L</hi>Eandro</persName> paid all.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Mil.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l rend="right">'Tis his usuall custome,</l>
                <l>And requisite he shoulde: he has now put off</l>
                <l>The Funerall black, (your rich heirs weares with joy,</l>
                <l>When he pretends to weep for his dead Father,)</l>
                <l>Your gathering Sires, so long heape muck together,</l>
                <l>That their kind Sonnes, to rid them of their care</l>
                <l>Wish them in <placeName>heaven</placeName>; Or if they take a taste</l>
                <l>Of <placeName>Purgatory</placeName> by the way, it matters not:</l>
                <l>Provided they remove hence; What is befalne</l>
                <l>To his Father, in the other world, I ask not,</l>
                <l>I am sure his prayre is heard: would I could use one</l>
                <l>For mine, in the same method.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italics">Arsen.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Fy upon thee.</l>
                <l>This is prophane,</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Mil.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Good Doctor, doe not schoole me,</l>
                <l>For a fault you are not free from: On my life</l>
                <l>Were all Heires in <placeName>Cordoba</placeName>, put too their oathes</l>
                <l>They would confesse with me, 'tis a sound Tenet:</l>
                <l>I am sure <persName>Leonardo</persName> do's.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italics">Ars.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>He is th' owner</l>
                <l>Of a faire Estate.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Mil.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>And fairly he deserves it,</l>
                <l>He's a royall Fellow: yet observes a meane</l>
                <l>In all his courses, carefull to on whom</l>
                <l>He showres his bounties: he that's liberall</l>
                <l>To all alike, may doe a Good by chance,</l>
                <l>But never out of Judgement: This invites</l>
                <l>The prime men of the Citie to frequent</l>
                <l>All places he resorts to, and are happy</l>
                <l>In his sweet Converse.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Ars.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l><persName><roleName>Don</roleName> Jaime</persName> the Brother</l>
                <l>To the Grandee <persName><roleName>Don</roleName> Henrique</persName>, appeares much taken</l>
                <l>With his behaviour. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Mil.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>There is something more in't:</l>
                <l>H<supplied resp="#mim" reason="damage" source="A">[e]</supplied> needs his Purse, and knowes how to make use on't,</l>
                <l><supplied resp="#mim" reason="damage" source="A">['Tis n]</supplied>ow in fashion your <persName><roleName>Don</roleName></persName>, that's poore,</l>
                <l>To vow all Leagues of friendship with a Merchant</l>
                <l>That can supply his wants, and howsoe're</l>
                <l><persName><roleName>Don</roleName> Jaime</persName>'s noble borne, his elder Brother</l>
                <l><persName><roleName>Don</roleName> Henrique</persName> rich, and his Revenues long since</l>
                <l>Encreasing by marrying with a wealthy Heire</l>
                <l>Call'd Madam <persName>Violante</persName>, he yet holds</l><note type="mansNote" resp="formerOwner" subtype="beReady">Jamy Leandro &amp; Ascanio be ready</note>
                <l>A hard hand o'er <persName>Jaime</persName>, allowing him</l>
                <l>A bare annuity onely.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Ars.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Yet 'tis said</l>
                <l>He hath no child, and by the Lawes of <placeName>Spaine</placeName></l>
                <l>If he die without issue, <persName><roleName>Don</roleName> Jaime</persName></l>
                <l>Inherits his Estate.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Mil.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Why that's the reason</l>
                <l>Of their so many jarres: Though the young Lord</l>
                <l>Be sick of the elder Brother, and in reason</l>
                <l>Should flatter, and observe him, he's of a nature</l>
                <l>Too bold, and fierce, to stoop so, but beares up,</l>
                <l>Presuming on his hopes.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Ars.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>What's the young Lad</l>
                <l>That all of em makes so much of?</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Mil.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>'Tis a sweet-One,</l>
                <l>And the best condition'd youth, I ever saw yet,</l>
                <l>So humble and so affable, that he wins</l>
                <l>The love of all that know him, and so modest,</l>
                <l>That (in despight of povertie) he would starve</l>
                <l>Rather then aske a courtesie; He's the Sonne</l>
                <l>Of a poore cast-Captaine, one <persName>Octavio</persName>,</l>
                <l>And She, that once was calld th' faire <persName>Iacinta</persName>,</l>
                <l>Is happy in being his Mother: for his sake.</l>
              </lg>
              <stage type= "entrance" place="center">Enter Jamie, Leandro, and Ascanio</stage><note type="mansNote" resp="formerOwner" subtype="crosshatchedLines">Cross-hatched lines.</note> 
              <lg>
                <l>(Though in their Fortunes falne) they are esteem'd of,</l>
                <l>And cherish'd by the best. O here they come,</l>
                <l>I now may spare his Character, but observe him,</l>
                <l>Hee'l justifie my report.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Ia.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>My good <persName>Ascanio</persName></l>
                <l>Repaire more often to me: above Women</l>
                <l>Thou ever shalt be welcome.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Asc.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>My Lord your favours</l>
                <l>May quickly teach a raw untutour'd Youth</l>
                <l>To be both rude and sawcie.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Leandro.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>You cannot be</l>
                <l>Too frequent, where you are so desir'd:</l>
                <l>And give me leave (dear friend) to be your Rivall</l>
                <l>In part of his Affection: I will buy it</l>
                <l>At any rate.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Ia.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Stood I but now possess'd</l>
                <fw type="catch">Of</fw>
                <pb n="TSC-002"
                  facs="https://digital.libraries.psu.edu/digital/collection/emblem/id/4382/rec/4"/>
                <fw type="pageNum">28</fw>
                <l>Of what my future hope presages to me,</l> 
                <l>I then would make it cleare thou hadst a Patron</l>
                <l>That would not say but do: yet as I am,</l>  
                <l>Be mine, I'le not receive thee as a servant,</l>  
                <l>But as my Son (and though I want my self)</l>
                <l>No Page attending in the Court of <placeName>Spain</placeName></l>  
                <l>Shall find a kinder master.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Ars.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I beseech you</l>
                <l>That my refusall of so great an offer</l>
                <l>May make no ill construction, ‘tis not pride</l>
                <l>(That common vice is farre from my condition)</l>
                <l>That makes you a denyall to receive</l>
                <l>A favour I should sue for: nor the fashion</l>
                <l>Which the <placeName>country</placeName> followes, in which to be a servant</l>
                <l>In those that groan beneath the heavy weight</l>
                <l>Of povertie is held an argument</l>
                <l>Of a base and abject mind, I wish my yeares</l>
                <l>Were fit to do you a service in a nature</l>
                <l>That might become a Gentleman (give me leave</l>
                <l>To think my self one) My father serv'd the King</l>
                <l>As a Captain in the field; and though his fortune</l>
                <l>Return'd him home a poore man, he was rich</l>
                <l>In reputation, and wounds fairly taken.</l>
                <l>Nor am I by his ill successe deterr'd,</l>
                <l>I rather feel a strong desire that swayes me</l>
                <l>To follow his Profession, and if <placeName>heaven</placeName></l>
                <l>Hath marked me out to be a man, how proud,</l>
                <l>In the service of my <placeName>Country</placeName>, should I be,</l>
                <l>To traile a pike under your brave command.</l>
                <l>There, I would follow you as a guid to honour,</l>
                <l>Though all the horrours of the Warre made up</l>
                <l>To stop my passage.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Ia.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Thou art a hopefull Boye,</l>
                <l>And it was bravely spoken: For this answer,</l>
                <l>I love thee more then ever.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Mil.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Pitty such seeds</l><note type="mansNote" resp="formerOwner" subtype="beReady">Henrique be ready</note>
                <l>Of promising courage should not grow and prosper</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>What ever his reputed Parents bee,</l>
                <l>He hath a mind that speakes him right and noble.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lea.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>You make him blush: it needs not sweet <persName>Ascanio</persName>,</l>
                <l>We may heare praises when they are deserv'd,</l>
                <l>Or modestie unwounded. By my life</l>
                <l>I would adde something to the building up</l>
                <l>So faire a mind, and if till you are fit</l>
                <l>To beare Armes in the field, you'l spend some yeares</l>
                <l>In <placeName>Salamanca</placeName>, I'le supply your studies</l>
                <l>With all conveniences.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Ars.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Your goodnesse (Signiors)</l>
                <l>And charitable favours overwhelm me.</l>
                <l>If I were of your blood, you could not be</l>
                <l>More tender of me: what then can I pay</l>
                <l>(A poore boy and a stranger) but a heart</l>
                <l>Bound to your service? with what willingnes</l>
                <l>I would receive (good Sir) your noble offer,</l>
                <l>Heaven can beare witnes for me: but alas</l>
                <l>Should I embrace the meanes to raise my fortunes,</l>
                <l>I must destroy the lives of my poore Parents</l>
                <l>(To whom I ow my being) they in me</l>
                <l>Place all their comforts, and (as if I were</l>
                <l>The light of their dim eyes) are so indulgent</l>
                <l>They cannot brook one short dayes absence from me;</l>
                <l>And (what will hardly win belief) though young,</l>
                <l>I am their steward and their nurse: the bounties</l>
                <l>VVhich others bestow on me serves to sustain ‘em,</l>
                <l>And to forsake them in their age, in me</l>
                <l>VVere more then murther.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <stage rend="center">Enter Henrique.</stage><note type="mansNote" resp="formerOwner" subtype="crosshatchedLines">Crossed-out cross-hatched lines.</note>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>This is a kind of begging</l>
                <l>VVould make a Broker charitable.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Mil.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Here (sweet heart)</l>
                <l>I wish that it were more.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lean.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>VVhen this is spent,</l>
                <l>Seek for supply from me</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Ja.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Thy pietie</l>
                <l>For ever be remembered: nay take all,</l>
                <l>Though 't were my exhibition to a Royall</l><note type="mansNote" subtype="crosshatchedlines" n="5">☨</note>
                <l>For one whole yeare.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Asc.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>High heavens reward your goodnes.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Hen.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>So Sir, is this a slip of your own grafting,</l>
                <l>You are so prodigall?</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Ia.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>A slip Sir?</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Hen.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Yes,</l>
                <l>A slip; or call it by the proper name</l>
                <l>Your Bastard.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Ia.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>You are foul-mouth'd; do not provoke me,</l>
                <l>I shall forget your Birth, if you proceed,</l>
                <l>And use you, (as your manners do deserve) uncivilly.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Hen.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>So brave? pray you give me hearing,</l>
                <l>Who am I Sir?</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Ia.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>My elder Brother: One</l>
                <l>That might have been born a fool and so reputed,</l>
                <l>But that you had the luck to creep into</l>
                <l>The world a yeare before me.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lean.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Be more temperate.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Ia.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I neither can nor will, unlesse I learn it</l>
                <l>By this example: let him use his harsh</l>
                <l>Unsavoury reprehensions upon those</l>
                <l>That are his hinds, and not on me. The <placeName>Land</placeName></l>
                <l>Our father left to him alone rewards him,</l>
                <l>For being twelve moneths elder, let that be</l>
                <l>Forgotten, and let his Parasites remember</l>
                <l>One quality of worth or vertue in him</l>
                <l>That may authorise him, to be a censurer</l>
                <l>Of me, or of my manners, and I will</l>
                <l>Acknowledge him for a tutor, til then, never</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Hen.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>From whom have you your meanes Sir?</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Ia.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>From the will</l>
                <l>Of my dead father; I am sure I spend not</l>
                <l>Nor give't upon your purse.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Hen.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>But will it hold out</l>
                <l>Without my help?</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Ia.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I am sure it shall I'le sink else</l>
                <l>For sooner I will seek aid from a whore,</l>
                <l>Then a courtesie from you.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Hen.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>'Tis well; you are proud of</l>
                <l>Your new Exchequer when you have cheated him</l>
                <l>And worn him to the quick, I may be found</l>
                <l>In the List of your acquaintance'</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lea.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Pray you hold</l>
                <l>And give me leave (my Lord) to say thus much</l>
                <l>(And in mine own defence) I am no Gull</l>
                <l>To be wrought on by perswasion: nor no Coward</l>
                <l>To be beaten out of my meanes, but know to whom</l>
                <l>And why I give or lend, and will do nothing</l>
                <l>But what my reason warrants; you may be</l>
                <l>As sparing as you please, I must be bold</l>
                <l>To make use of mine own, without your licence.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Ia.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>'Pray thee let him alone, he is not worthy thy an<supplied resp="#mim" reason="damage" source="a">[ger]</supplied></l>
                <l>All that he do's (<persName>Leandro</persName>) is for my good,</l>
                <l>I think there's not a Gentleman of <persName>Spain</persName>,</l>
                <l>That ha's a better steward, then I have of him.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Hen.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Your steward Sir?</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <fw type="sig">E2</fw>
            <fw type="catch" rend="italic">Ja.</fw>
            <pb n="TSC-003"
              facs="https://digital.libraries.psu.edu/digital/collection/emblem/id/4383/rec/4"/>
            <fw type="pageNum">27</fw>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Ja.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Yes, and a provident one:</l>
                <l>Why, he knowes I am given to large Expence,</l>
                <l>And therefore layes up for me: could you believe els</l>
                <l>That he, that sixteen years hath worne the yoke</l>
                <l>Of barren wedlock, without hope of issue,</l>
                <l>(His Coffer's full, his <placeName>Lands</placeName>, and <placeName>Vineyards</placeName> fruitfull)</l>
                <l>Could be so sold to base, and forbid thrift,</l>
                <l>As almost to deny himselfe, the meanes</l>
                <l>And necessaries of life? Alas, he knowes</l>
                <l>The Lawes of <placeName>Spaine</placeName> appoint me for his heire,</l>
                <l>That all must come to me, if I out-live him,</l>
                <l>(Which sure I must doe, by the course of Nature,)</l>
                <l>And the assistance of good Mirth, and Seck,</l>
                <l>How ever you prove Melancholy.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Hen.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>If I live,</l>
                <l>Thou dearly shalt repent this,</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Ja.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>When thou art dead,</l>
                <l>I am sure I shall not.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Mil.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Now they begin to burn</l>
                <l>Like oppos'd Meteors.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Ars.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Give them line, and way,</l>
                <l>My life for <persName><roleName>Don</roleName> Jamie</persName>.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Ja.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Continue still</l>
                <l>The excellent Husband, and joyne Farme to Farme,</l>
                <l>Suffer no Lordship, that in a cleare day</l>
                <l>Falls in the prospect of your coveteous eye</l>
                <l>To be an others; Forget you are a Grandee</l>
                <l>Take use upon use, and cut the throats of heires</l>
                <l>With cozening Mort-gages: rack your poore Tenants,</l>
                <l>Till they looke like so many Skeletons</l>
                <l>For want of Food; And when that Widowes curses,</l>
                <l>The ruines of ancient Families, teares of Orphans</l>
                <l>Have hurried you to the divell, ever remember</l>
                <l>All was rak'd up, for me, (your thankfull Brother)</l>
                <l>That will dance merrily upon your Grave,</l>
                <l>And perhaps give a double Pistolet</l>
                <l>To some poore needy Frier, to say a Masse</l>
                <l>To keep your Ghost from walking.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Hen.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>That the Law</l>
                <l>Should force me to endure this!</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Ia.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Verely,</l>
                <l>When this shall come to passe (as sure it will)</l>
                <l>If you can find a loope-hole, though in hell'</l>
                <l>To looke on my behaviour, you shall see me</l>
                <l>Ransack your Iron Chests, and once againe</l>
                <l><persName>Pluto</persName>'s flame-colour'd Daughter shall be free</l>
                <l>To dominier in <placeName>Taverns</placeName>, Maskes, and Revells</l>
                <l>As she was us'd before she was your Captive.</l>
                <l>Me thinkes the meere conceipt of it, should make you</l>
                <l>Goe <placeName>home</placeName> sick and distemper'd, if it do's,</l>
                <l>I'le send you a Doctor of mine owne, and after</l>
                <l>Take order for your Funerall.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Hen.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>You have said, sir,</l>
                <l>I will not fight with words, but deeds to tame you,</l>
                <l>Rest confident I will, and thou shalt wish</l>
                <l>This day thou hadst been dumb. --- </l>
              </lg>
              <stage type="exit">Exit.</stage>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Mil.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>You have given him a heat.</l>
                <l>But with your owne distemper.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Ia.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Not a whit</l>
                <l>Now he is from mine eye, I can be merry.</l>
                <l>Forget the cause, and him: all plagues goe with him</l>
                <l>Let's talke of something els: what newes is stirring?</l>
                <l>Nothing to passe the time?</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Mil.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>'Faith it is said</l>
                <l>That the next Summer will determine much</l>
                <l>Of that we long have talk'd of, touching the Wars.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lea.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>What have we to doe with them? Let us discourse</l>
                <l>Of what concerns our selves. 'Tis now in fashion</l>
                <l>To have you Gallants set downe, in a <placeName>Taverne</placeName>,</l>
                <l>What the Arch-Dukes purpose is the next spring &amp; what</l>
                <l>Defence my Lords (the States) prepare: what course</l>
                <l>The Emperour takes against the encroching Turke,</l>
                <l>And whither his Moony-Standards are design'd</l>
                <l>For <placeName>Persia</placeName>, or <placeName>Polonia</placeName>: and all this</l>
                <l>The wiser sort of State-Wormes seeme to know</l>
                <l>Better then their owne Affaires: this is discourse</l>
                <l>Fit for the Counsell it concerns; we are young,</l>
                <l>And if that I might give the Theame, 'twere better</l>
                <l>To talke of handsome women.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Mil.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>And that's one,</l>
                <l>Almost as generall.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Ars.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Yet none agree</l>
                <l>Who are the fairest.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lea.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Some prefer the French,</l>
                <l>For their conceited Dressings: some the plump</l>
                <l>Italian <hi rend="italic">Bona-Robas</hi>, some the State</l>
                <l>That ours observe; and I have heard one sweare,</l>
                <l>(A merry friend of mine) that once in <placeName>London</placeName>,</l>
                <l>He did enjoy the company of a Gamester</l>
                <l>(A common Gamester too) that in one night</l>
                <l>Met him th'Italian, French, and Spanish waies,</l>
                <l>And ended in the Dutch; for, to coole her selfe,</l>
                <l>She kiss'd him drunke in the morning.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Ia.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Wee may spare</l>
                <l>The travell of our tongues in forraigne Nations,</l>
                <l>When in <placeName>Corduba</placeName> if you dare give credit</l>
                <l>To my report (for I have seene her, Gallants)</l>
                <l>There lives a woman) of meane birth too,</l>
                <l>And meanly match'd) whose all-excelling Forme</l>
                <l>Disdaines comparison with any She</l>
                <l>That puts in for a faire one, and though you borrow</l>
                <l>From every <placeName>Country</placeName> of the <placeName>Earth</placeName> the best</l>
                <l>Of those perfections which the Clymat yeilds</l>
                <l>To help to make her up, if put in Ballance,</l>
                <l>This will weigh-downe the Scale.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lea.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>You talke of wonders.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Ia.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>She is indeed, a wonder, and so kept,</l>
                <l>And, as the world deserv'd not to behold</l>
                <l>What curious Nature made without a patterne,</l>
                <l>Whose Copy she hath lost too, she's shut up,</l>
                <l>Sequestred from the world.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lea.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Who is the owner</l>
                <l>Of such a Jem? I am fir'd.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Ia.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>One <persName>Bartolus</persName>,</l>
                <l>A wrangling Advocate.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Ars.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>A knave on Record.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Mil.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I am sure he cheated me of the best part</l>
                <l>Of my Estate.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Ia.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Some Businesse calls me hence,</l>
                <l>(And of importance) which denies me leisure</l>
                <l>To give you his full character: In few words</l>
                <l>(Though rich) he's covetous beyond expression,</l>
                <l>And to encrease his heape, will dare the Divell,</l>
                <l>And all the plagues of darknesse: and to these</l>
                <l>So jealous, as if you would paralell</l>
                <l>Old <persName>Argus</persName> to him, you must multiply</l>
                <l>His Eies and hundred times: of these, none sleepe.</l>
                <l>He that would charme the heaviest lid, must hire</l>
                <l>A better <persName>Mercurie</persName>, then <persName>Iove</persName> made use of:</l>
                <l>Blesse your selves from the thought of him and her</l>
                <l>For 'twill be labour lost: So farewell Signiors.---</l><stage type="exit">Exit.</stage>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Ars.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l><persName>Leandro</persName>? in a dreame? wake man, for shame.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <fw type="catch" rend="italic">Mil.</fw>
            <pb n="TSC-004"
              facs="https://digital.libraries.psu.edu/digital/collection/emblem/id/4384/rec/4"/>
            <fw type="pageNum">28</fw>
            <sp>
              <note type="mansNote" resp="#formerOwner" subtype="beReady">Octavio &amp; Jacinta be ready.</note><speaker>Mil.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Trayned into fooles <placeName>paradise</placeName> with a tale</l>
                <l>Of an imagin'd Forme,</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lea.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l><persName>Iamie</persName> is noble,</l>
                <l>And with a forg'd Tale would not wrong his Friend,</l>
                <l>Nor am I so much fired with lust as Envie,</l>
                <l>That such a churl as <persName>Bartolus</persName> should reap</l>
                <l>So sweete a har vest, half my State to any</l>
                <l>To help me a share.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Ars.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Tush do no hope for</l>
                <l>Impossibilities,</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lea.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I must enjoy her,</l>
                <l>And my prophetique love tells me I shall,</l>
                <l>Lend me but your assistance;</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Ars.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Give it 'ore,</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Mil.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I would not have thee fool'd</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lea.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I have strange Engines</l>
                <l>Fashioning here: and <persName>Bartolus</persName> on the Anville</l>
                <l>Diswade me not but help me,</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Mil.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Take your fortune,</l>
                <l>If you come off well; praise your wit, if not,</l>
                <l>Expect to be the subject of our Laughter.<stage type="exit" place="right">Exeunt.</stage></l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div xml:id="act1s2" type="scene" n="2">
            <head>
              <hi rend="italic">Scæna Secunda.</hi>
            </head>
            <stage type="entrance" place="center">Enter Octavio, and Iacinta.</stage><note type="mansNote" resp="#formerOwner" subtype="crosshatchedlines">Cross-hatched lines.</note>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Iac.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>You met <persName><roleName>Don</roleName> Henrique</persName>.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Yes:</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Iac.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>What comfort bring you?</l>
                <l>Speake cheerefully: how did my Letter worke?</l>
                <l>On his hard temper? I am sure I wrot it,</l>
                <l>So feelingly, and with the pen of sorrow,</l>
                <l>That it must force Compunction,</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>You are cozen'd;</l>
                <l>Can you with one hand prop a falling <placeName>Tower</placeName>?</l>
                <l>Or with the other stop theraging maine,</l>
                <l>When it breakes in on the usurped <placeName>Shore</placeName>?</l>
                <l>Or any thing that is impossible?</l>
                <l>And then conclude that there is some way left,</l>
                <l>To move him to compassion.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Iac.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Is there a Justice</l>
                <l>Or thunder (my <persName>Octavio</persName>) and he</l>
                <l>Not funk unto the center?</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Good <persName>Iacinta</persName>.</l>
                <l>With your long practised patience beare afflictions,</l>
                <l>And by provoking it call not on <placeName>Heavens</placeName> anger,</l>
                <l>He did not onely scrone to read your Letter,</l>
                <l>But (most inhumane as he is) he cursed you,</l>
                <l>Cursed you most bitterly,</l><note type="mansNote" resp="#formerOwner" subtype="beReady">Ascanio be ready.</note>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Iac.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>The bad mans charity,</l>
                <l>Oh that I could forget there were a Tye,</l>
                <l>In me upon him! or the releife I seeke,</l>
                <l>(If given) were bounty in him, and not debt,</l>
                <l>Debt of a deere accompt!</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Touch not that string,</l>
                <l>Twill but encrease your Sorrow, and tame silence,</l>
                <l>(The Balme of the oppressed) which hitherto</l>
                <l>Hath eas'd your grieved soule, and preserv'd your fame,</l>
                <l>Must be your Surgeon still.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Iac.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>If the contagion</l>
                <l>Of my misfortunes had not spread it self,</l>
                <l>Upon my Son <persName>Ascanio</persName>, though my wants</l>
                <l>Were centupli'd upon my self, I could be patient:</l>
                <l>But he is so good, I so miserable,</l>
                <l>His pious care his dutie, and obedience,</l>
                <l>And all that can be wish'd for from a Son,</l>
                <l>Discharg'd to me, and I, bard of all meanes,</l>
                <l>To returne any scruple of the debt</l>
                <l>I owe him as a Mother, is a Torment,</l>
                <l>Too painefull to be borne.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I suffer with you,</l>
                <l>In that; yet find in this assurance comfort,</l>
                <l>High <placeName>heavens</placeName> ordaines (whose purposes cannot alter)</l>
              </lg>
              <note type="mansNote" resp="#formerOwner" subtype="crosshatchedlines" place="left">Cross-hatched lines.</note>
              <stage type="entrance" place="center">Enter Ascanio.</stage>
              <note type="mansNote" resp="#formerOwner" subtype="crosshatchedlines" place="right">Cross-hatched lines.</note>
              <lg>
                <l>Children that pay obedience to their Parents,</l>
                <l>Shall never beg their Bread.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Iac.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Here comes our joy,</l>
                <l>Where has my dearest been?</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Asc.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I had made (Mother)</l>
                <l>A fortunate voyage and brought home rich prize,</l>
                <l>In a few houres: the owners too contented,</l>
                <l>From whom I tooke it. See heres Gold, good store too</l>
                <l>Nay, pray you take it,</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Iac.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Mens Charities are so cold,</l>
                <l>That if I knew not, thou wert made of Goodnes,</l>
                <l>'Twould breed a jealousie in me by what meanes,</l>
                <l>Thou cam'st by such a sum</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Asc.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Were it ill got,</l>
                <l>I am sure it could not be employed so well,</l>
                <l>As to relieve your wants. Some noble Friends,</l>
                <l>(Rais'd by <placeName>heavens</placeName> mercy to me, not my merits)</l>
                <l>Bestow'd it on me.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>It were a sacriledge</l>
                <l>To rob thee of their bounty, since they gave it,</l>
                <l>To thy use onely;</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Iac.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Buy thee brave Cloathes with it</l>
                <l>And fit thee for a fortune, and leave us,</l>
                <l>To our necessities; why do'st thou weep?</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Asc.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Out of my feare, I have offended you;</l>
                <l>For had I not, I am sure you are too kind,</l>
                <l>Not to accept the offer of my service,</l>
                <l>In which I am a gainer; I have heard</l>
                <l>My tutor say of all aiereall foule</l>
                <l>The Storke's the Embleme of true pietie,</l>
                <l>Because when age hath seiz'd upon her dam,</l>
                <l>And made unfit for flight, the gratefull young one</l>
                <l>Takes her upon his back, provides her foode,</l>
                <l>Repaying so, her tender care of him,</l><note type="mansNote" resp="#formerOwner" subtype="beReady">Hen: &amp; Viol: be ready.</note>
                <l>'Ere he was fit to fly, by bearing her:</l>
                <l>Shall I then that have reason, and discourse</l>
                <l>That tell me all I can doe is too litle,</l>
                <l>Be more unnaturall then a silly Bird?</l>
                <l>Or feed or cloth my selfe superfluously,</l>
                <l>And know, nay see you want? holy Saints keepe me.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Iac.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Can I be wretched,</l>
                <l>And know my selfe the Mother to such Goodnes?</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Come, let us drie our eyes, wee'll have a Feast,</l>
                <l>Thanks to our little Steward;</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Iac.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>And in him,</l>
                <l>Beleeve that we are rich.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Asc.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I am sure I am,</l>
                <l>While I have power to comfort you, and serve you.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <stage type="exit" place="right">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div xml:id="act1s3" type="scene" n="3">
            <head>
              <hi rend="italic">Scæa Tertia.</hi>
            </head>
            <stage type="entrance" place="center">Enter Henrique and Violante.</stage><note type="mansNote" resp="#formerOwner" subtype="crosshatchedlines">Cross-hatched lines.</note>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Is it my fault, (<persName><roleName>Don</roleName> Henrique</persName>) or my fate,</l>
                <l>Wha'ts my offence? I came young to your <placeName>Bed</placeName></l>
                <l>I had a fruitfull Mother, and you met me,</l>
                <l>With equall ardour in your May of blood;</l>
                <l>And why then am I barren?</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <fw type="catch" rend="italic">Hen.</fw>
            <pb n="TSC-005"
              facs="https://digital.libraries.psu.edu/digital/collection/emblem/id/4385/rec/4"/>
            <fw type="pageNum">29</fw>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Hen.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>'Tis not in Man</l>
                <l>To yield a reason for the will of Heaven,</l>
                <l>Which is inscrutable.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>To what use serve</l>
                <l>Full fortunes, and the meaner sort of Blessings,</l>
                <l>When that, which is the Crowne of all our wishes,</l>
                <l>The period of humane happines,</l>
                <l>One only Child that may possesse what's ours,</l>
                <l>Is cruelly denide us?</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Hen.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>'Tis the curse,</l>
                <l>Of great Estates to want those Pledges which,</l>
                <l>The poore are happy in: They in a <placeName>Cottage</placeName>,</l>
                <l>With joy, behold the Modells of their youth,</l>
                <l>And as their Roote decaies those budding Branches,</l>
                <l>Sprout forth and flourish, to renew their age;</l>
                <l>But this is the beginning not the end</l>
                <l>To me, of, that misery against my will,</l>
                <l>(Since <placeName>Heaven</placeName> denies us Issue of our owne)</l>
                <l>Must leave the fruit of all my care and travell</l>
                <l>To an unthankfull Brother that insults,</l>
                <l>On my Calamity.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I will rather choose,</l>
                <l>A Bastard from the <placeName>Hospitall</placeName> and adopt him,</l>
                <l>And nourish him, as mine owne.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Hen.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Such an evasion</l>
                <l>(My <persName>Violante</persName>) is forbid to us;</l>
                <l>Happy the <placeName>Romane State</placeName>, where it was lawfull,</l>
                <l>(If our owne Sonnes were vicious) to choose one</l>
                <l>Out of a vertuous Stock, though of poore Parents,</l>
                <l>And make him noble. But the Lawes of <placeName>Spaine</placeName>,</l>
                <l>(Intending to preserve all ancient Houses)</l>
                <l>Prevent such free elections; with this my Brothers</l>
                <l>Too well acquainted and this makes him bold to</l>
                <l>Reigne ‘ore me, as a Master,</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I will fire</l>
                <l>The Portion I brought with me, ‘ere he spend,</l>
                <l>A Royall of it: No Quirck left? no Quiddit</l>
                <l>That may defeate him?</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Hen.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Were I but confirmed,</l>
                <l>That you would take the meanes I use, with patience,</l>
                <l>As I must practise it with my dishonour,</l>
                <l>I could lay levell with the earth his hopes</l>
                <l>That soare above the clouds with expectation</l>
                <l>To see me in my <placeName>grave</placeName>.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Effect but this</l>
                <l>And our revenge shall be to us a Son</l>
                <l>That shall inherit for us.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Hen.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Do not repent</l>
                <l>When ‘tis too late.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I feare not what may fall</l>
                <l>He disposess'd that doe's usurpe on all</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <stage type="exit" place="right">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
      </div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
