<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title xml:id="TSC">THE SPANISH CURATE</title>
        <author>John Fletcher</author>
        <author>Philip Massinger</author>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Edited and encoded by:</resp>
          <name xml:id="mim">Maria Isabel Maza</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Published by the Open Publishing Unit of The Pennsylvania State University Libraries.</publisher>
        <availability>
          <p>Attribution 4.0 International (CC BY 4.0)</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <seriesStmt>
        <title>The Digital Beaumont &amp; Fletcher (1647) Project</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor:</resp>
          <name xml:id="cmlb">Claire M.L. Bourne</name>
        </respStmt> 
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Project Manager:</resp>
          <name xml:id="hf">Heather Froehlich</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Text Encoding Consultant:</resp>
          <name xml:id="jr">John Russell</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Open Publishing Program Coordinator</resp>
          <name>Ally Laird</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Open Access Systems Developer</resp>
          <name xml:id="ag">Andrew Gearhart</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Graduate Assistants:</resp>
          <name>Taylor Hare</name>
          <name>David LeBlanc</name>
          <name>Danielle Ryle</name>
          <name>Lauren Cenci</name>
          <name>Maria Isabel Maza</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Annotator(s)</resp>
          <name xml:id="formerOwner">Former Owner - Author of Handwritten Annotations</name>
        </respStmt>
      </seriesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>Francis Beaumont</author>
            <author>John Fletcher</author>
            <title>Comedies and Tragedies Written by Francis Beavmont and Iohn Fletcher,
              Gentlemen. Never printed before, And now published by the Authours
              Originall Copies.</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Humprey Robinson</publisher>
              <publisher>the three Pidgeons</publisher>
              <publisher>Humphrey Moseley</publisher>
              <pubPlace>The Prince Armes in St. Pauls Church-yard</pubPlace>
              <date>1647</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier xml:id="psf">
            <country>The United States</country>
            <region>Pennsylvania</region>
            <institution>Pennsylvania State University</institution>
            <repository>Eberly Family Special Collections Library</repository>
            <collection>Emblem Books</collection>
            <msName>COMEDIES AND TRAGEDIES</msName> 
            <msName> 
              <rs>
                3083972
              </rs>
            </msName>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>This document is a simplified "true-to-text" XML version of <title>The Spanish Curate</title> based on Pennsylvania State University's annotated copy of the 1647
        Beaumont &amp; Fletcher first folio. Major textual elements and attributes have been captured based on how they appear in the folio. Whenever possible, editorial
        interventions have been minimalized or avoided entirely. This document is meant to serve as a pedagogical tool by which students of Early Modern literature can learn
        to construct edited XML versions of the play.</p>    
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          The Digital Beaumont &amp; Fletcher (1647) is a collaborative editorial project aimed at making many of the rarely edited—and, as a result, rarely taught—plays in the
          “Beaumont &amp; Fletcher” canon accessible to student readers and freely available online for classroom use. This project was inspired by the distinctive copy of Comedies
          and Tragedies Written by Francis Beavmont And Iohn Fletcher Gentlemen (1647) held by Penn State University's Eberly Family Special Collections Library. In addition to
          preserving evidence of ownership dating to as early as 1703, Penn State's copy of this printed play collection also includes three plays with handwritten marginalia,
          suggesting that the book might have been used to facilitate performance in the late seventeenth century. This project is also motivated by a desire to make the texts and
          other features of this book more widely known and readable. As a first step, the whole volume has now been fully digitized, thanks to the department of Preservation,
          Conservation, and Digitization at Penn State Libraries.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Provides details of editorial principles and practices applied during the encoding of a text</p>
        <correction>
          <p>
            This transcription copies almost exactly the text from Penn State's copy of the first folio. Moderniztions in certain letters were followed (I for J, VV for W, etc.) 
            Obivous errors were corrected (upside down letters (n for a u, I for l, etc.). Manuscript notes are included in the transcription, placed as closely as possible to the
            original placement on the page. For further details about editoral principles, please consult the project website. 
          </p>
        </correction>
        <normalization source="OED">
          <p>ALL words converted to Modern British spelling 
            following Oxford English Dictionary.</p>
        </normalization>
        <punctuation>
          <p>Punctuation was modernized to register full syntactical units.</p>
        </punctuation>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <handNotes>
        <handNote>
          <p>
            This edition of The Spanish Curate contains the manuscript notes found in the Penn State Libraries' copy of the 1647 folio. These manuscript notes are particually attentive to
            the performance of the play, and prepare actors for entrances and emphasize stage directions throughout the text. For more information on these manuscript notes, consult 
            the editorial principles and the introduction to <title>The Spanish Curate</title>.
          </p>
        </handNote>
      </handNotes>
      <langUsage>
        <p>chracters for marginal notes?</p>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="act3">
          <div xml:id="act3s1" type="scene" n="1">
            <head>
              <hi rend="italic">Actus Tertius, Scæna Prima.</hi>
            </head>
            <stage type="entrance" place="center">Enter Henrique and Bartolus.</stage>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Hen.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>You know my cause sufficiently?</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I doe (Sir.)</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Hen.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>And though it will impaire my honesty,</l>
                <l>And strike deep at my Credit, yet (my <persName>Bartolus</persName>)</l>
                <l>There being no other evasion left to free me</l>
                <l>From the vexation of my spightfull Brother,</l>
                <l>That most insultingly raignes over me,</l>
                <l>I must and will goe forward.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Doe (my Lord)</l>
                <l>And looke not after credit, we shall cure that,</l>
                <l>Your bended honestie, we shall set right (Sir)</l>
                <l>We Surgeons of the Law, doe desperate cures (Sir)</l>
                <l>And you shall see how heartily I'll handle it:</l>
                <l>Marke how I'll knock it home: be of good cheare (Sir)</l>
                <l>You give good Fees, and those beget good Causes,</l>
                <l>The prerogative of your crownes will carry the matter,</l>
                <l>(Carry it sheere) The <persName>Assistant</persName> sits to morrow,</l>
                <l>And he's your friend, your monied men love naturally,</l>
                <l>And as your love are cleare, so are your Causes.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Hen.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>He shall not want for that.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>No, no, he must not,</l>
                <l>Line your Cause warmly (Sir) the times are Aguish,</l>
                <l>That holds a Plea in heart; hand the penurious,</l>
                <l>Their Causes (like their purses) have poore Issues.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Hen.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>That way, I was ever bountifull.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>'Tis true (Sir)</l>
                <l>That makes ye fear'd, forces the Snakes to kneele to ye,</l>
                <l>Live full of money, and supply the Lawyer,</l>
                <l>And take your choice of what <placeName>mans lands</placeName> you please (Sir)</l>
                <l>What pleasures, or what profits; what revenges,</l>
                <l>They are all your owne: I must have witnesses</l>
                <l>Enough, and ready.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Hen.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>You shall not want (my <persName>Bartolus</persName>.)</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Substantiall fearless soules, that wil swear suddenly,</l>
                <l>That will sweare any thing.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Hen.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>They shall sweare truth too.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>That's no great matter: for varietie</l>
                <l>They may sweare truth, els 'tis not much look'd after:</l>
                <l>I will serve Processe, presently, and strongly</l>
                <l>Upon your Brother, and <persName>Octavio</persName>,</l>
                <l><persName>Jacintha</persName>, and the Boy; provide your proofes (Sir)</l>
                <l>And set 'em fairely off, be sure of Witnesses,</l>
                <l>Though they cost money, want no store of witnesses,</l>
                <l>I have seen a handsome Cause, so fowly lost (Sir,)</l>
                <l>So beastly cast away for want or Witnesses.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Hen.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>There shall want nothing.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Then be gone, be provident,</l>
                <l>Send to the Judge, a secret way: you have me,</l>
                <l>And let him understand the heart.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Hen.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I shall (Sir.)</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>And feele the pulses strongly beat, I'll study,</l>
                <l>And at my houre, but mark me, goe, be happy,</l>
                <l>Goe, and beleeve i'th'Law.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Hen.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I hope 'twill helpe me.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <stage type="exit" place="right" rend="indent">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div xml:id="act3s2" type="scene" n="2">
            <head>
              <hi rend="italic">Scæna Secunda</hi>
            </head>
            <stage>Enter Lopez, Diego, and foure Parishioners and Singers.</stage>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lop.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Nea'r talke to me, I will not stay amongst ye,</l>
                <l>Debaushe'd and ignorant lazie knaves I found ye,</l>
                <l>And fooles I leave ye, I have taught these twenty yeares,</l>
                <l>Preacht spoon-meat to ye, that a child might swallow,</l>
                <l>Yet ye are Block-heads still: what should I say to ye?</l>
                <l>Ye have neither faith, nor money left to save ye,</l>
                <l>Am I fit companion for such Beggers?</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>1.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>If the Shepheard will suffer the sheep to be scab'd (Sir)</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lop.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>No, no, ye are rotten.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Di.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Would they were, for my sake.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lop.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I have nointed ye, and tar'd ye with my doctrine,</l>
                <l>And yet the murren sticks to ye, yet ye are mangy,</l>
                <l>I will avoid ye.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <stage type="business" place="right">Two chaires set out.</stage>
            <sp>
              <speaker>2.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>'Pray ye (Sir) be not angry,</l>
                <l>In the pride of your new Cassock, doe not part with us,</l>
                <l>We doe acknowledge ye a carefull Curat,</l>
                <l>And one that seldome troubles us with Sermons,</l>
                <l>A short slice of a Reading serves us (Sir)</l>
                <l>We doe acknowledge ye a quiet Teacher,</l>
                <l>Before You'll vex your Audience, you'll sleep with 'em,</l>
                <l>And that's a loving thing.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>3.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>We grant ye (Sir)</l>
                <l>The onely benefactor to our Bowling,</l>
                <l>To all our merry Sports, the first provoker,</l>
                <l>And at our Feasts, we know there is no reason,</l>
                <l>But you that edifie us most, should eat most.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lop.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I will not stay for all of this, ye shall know me</l>
                <l>A man borne to a more beseeming fortune</l>
                <l>Then ringing all-in, to a rout of Dunces.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>4.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>We will increase your Tithes, you shall have Egs too,</l>
                <l>Though they may prove most dangerous to our Issues.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>1.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I am a Smith; yet thus far out of my love</l>
                <l>You shall have the tenth horse I prick, to pray for,</l>
                <l>I am sure I prick five hundred in a yeare (Sir.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>2.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I am a Cooke, a man of dride conscience,</l>
                <l>et thus far I relent: you shall have tith porrage.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>3.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Your stipend shal be rais'd (good neighbour <persName>Die<lb rend="turnunder"/>go</persName></l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Di.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Would ye have me speak for ye? I am more angry</l>
                <l>Ten times more vex'd, not to be pacified:</l>
                <l>No, there be other places for poore Sextons</l>
                <l>Places of profit (Friends) find stirring places,</l>
                <l>And people that know how to use our Offices,</l>
                <l>Know what they were made for: I speak for such Capons?</l>
                <l>Ye shall find the Key o'th' <placeName>Church</placeName>,</l>
                <l>Under the doore (Neighbours,)</l>
                <fw type="catch">You</fw>
                <pb n="TSC-011"
                  facs="https://digital.libraries.psu.edu/digital/collection/emblem/id/4391/rec/4"/>
                <fw type="sig">F2</fw>
                <fw type="pageNum">35</fw>
                <l>You may goe in, and drive away the dawes.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lop.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>My Surplesse, with one sleeve, you shall find there,</l>
                <l>For to that dearth of Linnen, you have driven me;</l>
                <l>And the old Cutworke Cope, that hangs by gymitrie:</l>
                <l>'Pray ye turne em carefully, they are very tender:</l>
                <l>The remnant of the Books, lie where they did (Neigh<lb rend="turnunder"/>bours</l>
                <l>Half puft away with the Church-wardens pipings.</l>
                <l>Such smoaky zeales they have against hard places,</l>
                <l>The poore-mans Box is there too: if ye find any thing</l>
                <l>Besides the posie, and that halfe rub'd out too,</l>
                <l>For feare it should awake too much charitie</l>
                <l>Give it to pious uses, that is, spend it:</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Die.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>The Bell-ropes, they are strong enough to hang ye,</l>
                <l>So we bequeath ye to your destiny.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>1.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Pray ye be not so hastie.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Di.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I'll speake a proud word to ye,</l>
                <l>Would ye have us stay?</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>2.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>We doe most hearilty pray ye.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>3.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I'll draw as mighty drinke (Sir.)</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lop.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>A strong motive,</l>
                <l>The stronger still the more ye come unto me.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>3.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>And I'll send for my Daughter:</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lop.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>This may stir too:</l>
                <l>The Madien is of age, and must be edified.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>4.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>You shall have any thing: loose our learned Vicar?</l>
                <l>And our most constant friend; honest deare <persName>Diego</persName>?</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Di.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Yet all this will not do: I'll tell ye (Neighbours)</l>
                <l>And tell ye true: if ye will have us stay,</l>
                <l>If you will have the comforts of our companies,</l>
                <l>You shall be bound to doe us right in these points,</l>
                <l>You shall be bound, and this the obligation,</l>
                <l>Dy when 'tis fit, that we may have fit duties</l>
                <l>And doe not seeke to draw—out our undoings,</l>
                <l>Marry tryde women, that are free and fruitfull,</l>
                <l>Get children in abundance, for your Christnings,</l>
                <l>Or suffer to be got, 'tis equall justice,</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lop.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Let Weddings, Christnings, Churchings, Funerals,</l>
                <l>And merry Gossippings goe round, go round still,</l>
                <l>Round as a Pig, that we may find the profit.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Die.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>And let your old men fall sick handsomely:</l>
                <l>And dy immediatly, their Sonnes may shoot up:</l>
                <l>Let women dy oth'sullens too, 'tis naturall,</l>
                <l>But be sure their Daughters be of age first,</l>
                <l>That they may stock us still: your queazie young wives</l>
                <l>That perish undeliver'd, I am vext with,</l>
                <l>And vext abundantly, it much concerns me,</l>
                <l>There's a childes buriall lost, looke that be mended.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Let 'em be brought to bed, then dy when they please,</l>
                <l>These things considered (Country-men) and sworne to</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>2.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>All these, and all our sports againe, and gambolls.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>3.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>We must dy, and we must live, and we'll be merry,</l>
                <l>Every man shall be rich by one another.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>2.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>We are here tomorrow, and gone today: for my part</l>
                <l>If getting children can be-friend my Neighbours,</l>
                <l>I'll labour hard but I will fill your Font ( Sir.)</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>1.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I have a Mother now, and an old Father,</l>
                <l>They are as sure your own, within these two moneths—</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>4.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>My Sister must be prayd for too, she is desperate,</l>
                <l>Desperate in love.</l><note type="mansNote" resp="#formerOwner" subtype="beReady">Arseno &amp; Millanes be ready</note>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Die.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Keepe, desperate men farre from her,</l>
                <l>Then 'twill goe hard: doe you see how melancholy?</l>
                <l>Doe you marke the man? do you professe ye love him?</l>
                <l>And would doe any thing to stay his fury?</l>
                <l>And are ye unprovided to refresh him,</l>
                <l>To make him know your loves? fie Neighbours,</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>2.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>We'll doe any thing,</l>
                <note type="mansNote" resp="#formerOwner" subtype="beReady">Bar &amp; ready on the table</note><note type="mansNote" resp="#formerOwner" subtype="beReady">Dance be ready</note><l>We have brought Musick to appease his spirit,</l>
                <l>And the best Song we'll give him.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Die.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>'Pray ye sit down (Sir)</l>
                <l>They know their duties now, and they stand ready</l>
                <l>To tender their best mirth.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lop.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>'Tis well, proceed Neighbours,</l>
                <l>I am glad I have brought ye to understand good manners,</l>
                <l>Ye had Puritan hearts a-while, spurn'd at all pastimes,</l>
                <l>But I see some hope now.</l><note type="mansNote" resp="#formerOwner" subtype="action">Dance.</note><note type="mansNote" resp="#formerOwner" subtype="crosshatchedlines">Cross-hatched lines.</note>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Die.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>We are set proceed Neighbours.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <stage type="entrance" place="center">Enter Arsenio and Millanes.</stage><note type="mansNote" resp="#formerOwner" subtype="crosshatchedlines">Cross-hatched lines.</note>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Ars.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l rend="right">(it?</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Ars.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>What ayles this Priest? how highly the thing takes</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Mi.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Lord how it looks? has he not bought some Prebend?</l>
                <l><persName>Leandro</persName>'s money, makes the Rascall merry,</l>
                <l>Merry at heart; he spies us.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp><stage type="business" place="right">(Table.</stage>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Be gon Neighbours,</l><stage type="business" place="right">The Bar &amp; Book ready on a</stage><note type="mansNote" resp="#formerOwner" subtype="crosshatchedlines">Cross-hatched lines.</note>
                <l>Here are some Gentlemen: be gone good Neighbours,</l>
                <l>Be gone, and labour to redeeme my favour,</l>
                <l>No more words, but be gon: these two are Gnetlemen,</l>
                <l>No company for crusty-handed fellowes.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Dieg.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>We will stay for a yeare or two, and trie ye:</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lop.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Fill all your hearts with joy, we will stay with ye,</l>
                <l>Be gone, no more; I take your pastimes graciously:</l>
                <l>Would ye with me (my friends?)</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Ars.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>We would looke upon ye,</l>
                <l>For me-thinks ye looke lovely.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lop.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Ye have no Letters?</l>
                <l>Nor any kind of Remembrances?</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Mil.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Remembrances?</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lop.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>From <placeName>Nova Hispania</placeName>, or some part remote (Sir)</l>
                <l>You looke like travell'd men: may be some old friends</l>
                <l>That happily I have forgot; some Signeours</l>
                <l>In <placeName>China</placeName> or <placeName>Cataya</placeName>; some Companions—</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Dieg.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>In the <placeName>Mogulls Court</placeName>, or else-where.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Ars.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>They are mad sure.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lop.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Ye came not from <placeName>Peru</placeName>? doe they look (<persName>Diego</persName>)</l>
                <l>As if they had some mistery about em?</l>
                <l>Another <persName><roleName>Don</roleName> Alonzo</persName> now?</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Di.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I marry,</l>
                <l>And so much money, Sir, from one you know not,</l>
                <l>Let it be who it will.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lop.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>They have gracious favours.</l>
                <l>Would ye be private?</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Mil.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>There's no need on't (Sir)</l>
                <l>We come to bring ye a Remembrance from a Merchant.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lop.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>'Tis very well, 'tis like I know him.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Ars.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>No, sir,</l>
                <l>I doe not thinke ye doe.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lop.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>A new mistake (<persName>Diego</persName>)</l>
                <l>Let's carry it decently.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Ars.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>We come to tell ye,</l>
                <l>You have received great summes from a young Factor</l>
                <l>They call <persName>Leandro</persName>, that has rob'd his Master,</l>
                <l>Rob'd him, and run away.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Dieg.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Let's keep close ( Master)</l>
                <l>This newes comes from a cold <placeName>Country</placeName>.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lop.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>By my faith it freezes,</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Mil.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l rend="right">Curate)</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Mil.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Is not this true? doe you shrink now (good man</l>
                <l>Doe I not touch ye?</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lop.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>We have a hundred Duckets</l>
                <l>Yet left, we doe beseech ye sir—</l><note type="mansNote" resp="#formerOwner" subtype="beReady">octa: Jacin &amp; Ascanio be ready</note>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Mil.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>You'll hang both.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lop.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>One may suffice.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Di.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I will not hang alone ( Master)</l>
                <l>I had the least part, you shall hang the highest,</l>
                <l>Plague o' this <persName>Tiveria</persName>, and the Letter</l>
                <fw type="catch">The</fw>
                <pb n="TSC-012"
                  facs="https://digital.libraries.psu.edu/digital/collection/emblem/id/4392/rec/4"/>
                <fw type="pageNum">36</fw>
                <l>The <persName>divell</persName> sent it, post, to pepper us,</l>
                <l>From <placeName>Nova Hispania</placeName> we shall hang at home now.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Ars.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I see ye are penitent, and I have compassion:</l>
                <l>Ye are secure both; doe but what we charge ye,</l>
                <l>Ye shall have more gold too, and he shall give it,</l>
                <l>Ye ne're indanger ye.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lop.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Command us (Master)</l>
                <l>Command us presently, and see how nimbly—</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Die.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>And if we doe not handsomely endeavour—</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Ars.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Goe home and till ye heare more keep private,</l>
                <l>Till we appeare againe, no words, (Vicar)</l>
                <l>There's something added.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Mil.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>For you too.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lop.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>We are ready.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Mil.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Goe, and expect us hourely, if ye falter,</l>
                <l>Though ye had twenty lives—</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Die.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>We are fit to loose 'em.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lop.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>'Tis most expedient that we should hang both.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Die.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>If we be hang'd, we cannot blame our fortune.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Mil.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Farewell, and be your owne friends.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lop,</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>We expect ye.—</l>
              </lg>
            </sp><stage type="exit" place="right">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div xml:id="act3s3" type="scene" n="3">
            <head>
              <hi rend="italic">Scæna Tertia.</hi>
            </head>
            <stage>Enter Octavio, Jacintha, Ascanio.</stage><note type="mansNote" resp="#formerOwner" subtype="crosshatchedlines">Cross-hatched lines.</note>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>We cited to the Court!</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <stage type="business" place="right">A Bar. Table-booke,</stage>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Ja.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>It is my wonder,</l>
              </lg>
            </sp><stage type="business" place="right">2 chairs, &amp; paper standish</stage>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>But not our fear, (<persName>Iacintha</persName>) wealthy men,</l><stage type="business" place="right">(set out.</stage>
                <l>That have Estates to loose, whose conscious thoughts</l>
                <l>Are full of inward guilt, may shake with horrour,</l>
                <l>To have their Actions sifted, or appeare</l><note type="mansNote" resp="#formerOwner" subtype="beReady">Jamy &amp; bar: be ready</note>
                <l>Before the Judge. But we that know our selves</l>
                <l>As innocent, as poore, that have no Fleece</l>
                <l>On which the Talons of the gripping Law</l>
                <l>Can take sure hold, may smile with scorne on all</l>
                <l>That can be urg'd against us.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Ia.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I am confident</l>
                <l>There is no man so covetous, that desires</l>
                <l>To ravish our wants from us, and lesse hope</l>
                <l>There can be so much Justice left on <placeName>earth</placeName>,</l>
                <l>(Though sude, and call'd upon) to ease us of</l>
                <l>The burthen of our wrongs.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>What thinkes <persName>Ascanio</persName>?</l>
                <l>Should we be call'd in question or accus'd</l>
                <l>Unjustly, what would you doe to redeeme us,</l>
                <l>From tirannous oppression?</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Asc.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I could pray</l>
                <l>To him that ever has an open eare</l>
                <l>To heare the innocent, and right their wrongs;</l>
                <l>Nay, by my tr[ ]th, I thinke I could plead</l>
                <l>An Advocate, and sweat as much as he</l>
                <l>Do's for a double Fee, ere you should suffer</l>
                <l>In an honest cause.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <stage type="entrance" place="center">Enter Iamie and Bartolus.</stage><note type="mansNote" resp="#formerOwner" subtype="crosshatchedlines">Cross-hatched lines.</note>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Happy simplicitie!</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Ia.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>My dearest, and my best one: <persName><roleName>Don</roleName> Iaime</persName>,</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>And the Advocate, that caus'd us to be summond.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Asc.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>My Lord is mov'd, I see it in his lookes,</l>
                <l>And that man, in the Gowne, in my opinion</l>
                <l>Lookes like a proaguing knave.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Iac.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Peace, give them leave.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Iam.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Serve me with Processe?</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>My Lord, you are not lawlesse.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Iam.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Nor thou honest;</l>
                <l>One, that not long since was the buckram Scribe,</l>
                <l>That would run on mens errands for an Asper,</l>
                <l>And from such basenesse, having rais'd a Stock</l>
                <l>To bribe the covetous Judge call'd to the Bar,</l>
                <l>So poore in practise too, that you would plead</l>
                <l>A needy Clyents Cause, for a starv'd hen,</l>
                <l>Or halfe a little loyn of Veale, though fly-blowne,</l>
                <l>And these, the greatest Fees you could arrive at</l>
                <l>For just proceedings; but since you turn'd Rascall—</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Good words, my Lord</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Iam.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>And grew my Brothers Bawd</l>
                <l>In all his vitious courses, soothing him</l>
                <l>In his dishonest practises, you are growne</l>
                <l>The rich, and eminent knave, in the <persName>divels</persName> name,</l>
                <l>What am I cited for?</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>You shall know anon,</l>
                <l>And then too late repent this bitter language,</l>
                <l>Or I'll misse of my ends.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Iam.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Wer't not in <placeName>Court</placeName>,</l>
                <l>I would beat that fat of thine, rais'd by the food</l>
                <l>Snatch'd from poore Clyents mouthes, into a jelly:</l>
                <l>I would (my man of Law) but I am patient,</l>
                <l>And would obey the Judge.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>'Tis your best course:</l>
                <l>Would every enemy I have would beat me,</l>
                <l>I would wish no better Action.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>'Save your Lordship.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Asc.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>My humble service.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Iam.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>My good Boy, how dost thou?</l>
                <l>Why art thou call'd into the <placeName>Court</placeName>?</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <stage type="entrance" place="center">Enter Assistant, Henrique, Officer, and Witnesses.</stage>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Asc.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I know not,</l>
                <l>But 'tis my Lord the <persName>Assistants</persName> pleasure</l>
                <l>I should attend here.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Iam.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>He will soone resolve us.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Offic.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Make way there for the <persName>Judge</persName>.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Jam.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>How? my kind Brother?</l>
                <l>Nay then 'tis ranck: there is some villany towards.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Assist.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>'Tis Sessions purchas'd at your suit, <persName><roleName>Don</roleName> Henrique</persName>,</l>
                <l>Hath brought us hither, to heare and determine</l>
                <l>Of what you can prefer.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Henrique.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I doe beseech</l>
                <l>The honourable Court, I may be heard</l>
                <l>In my Advocate.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Assist.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>'Tis granted.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>humh, humh.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Jam.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>That preface</l>
                <l>If left out in a Lawyer, spoyles the Cause,</l>
                <l>Though ne're so good, and honest.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>If I stood here,</l>
                <l>To plead in the defence of an ill man,</l>
                <l>(Most equall Judge) or to accuse the innocent</l>
                <l>(To both which, I professe my selfe a stranger)</l>
                <l>I would be requisite I should deck my Language</l>
                <l>With Tropes and Figures, and all flourishes</l>
                <l>That grace a Rethorician, 'tis confess'd</l>
                <l>Adulterate Mettals, need the Gold-smiths Art,</l>
                <l>To set 'em off; what, in it selfe is perfect</l>
                <l>Contemnes a borrowed glosse: This Lord (my Client)</l>
                <l>Whose honest cause, when 'tis related truly,</l>
                <l>Will challenge Justice, finding in his conscience</l>
                <l>A tender scruple of a fault long since</l>
                <l>By him committed, thinkes it not sufficent</l>
                <l>To be absolv'd of't, by his Confessor,</l>
                <l>If that in open Court, he publish not</l>
                <l>What so long conceal'd.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <fw type="catch" rend="italic">Jam.</fw>
            <pb n="TSC-013"
              facs="https://digital.libraries.psu.edu/digital/collection/emblem/id/4393/rec/4"/>
            <fw type="pageNum">37</fw>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Iam.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>To what tends this?</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>In his young yeares (it is no miracle</l>
                <l>That youth, and heat of Blood, should mix together)</l>
                <l>He look'd upon this woman, on whose face</l>
                <l>The ruines yet remaine, of excellent forme,</l>
                <l>He look'd on her, and lov'd her.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Iac.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>You good <persName>Angels</persName>,</l>
                <l>What an imprudence is this?</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>And us'd all meanes</l>
                <l>Of Service, Courtship, Presents, that might win her</l>
                <l>To be at his devotion: but in vaine</l>
                <l>Her maiden Fort, impregnable held out</l>
                <l>Untill he promis'd Marriage; and before</l>
                <l>These Witnesses a solemne Contract pass'd</l>
                <l>To take her as his wife.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Assist.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Give them their oath.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Iam.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l rend="right">(tures,</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Iam.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>They are incompetent Witnesses, his own Crea-</l>
                <l>And will sweare any thing for halfe a royall.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Off.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Silence.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Assist.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Proceed.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Upon this strong assurance</l>
                <l>He did enjoy his wishes to the full,</l>
                <l>Which satisfied, and then with eyes of Judgement</l>
                <l>(Had winck'd with lust before) considering duly</l>
                <l>The inequality of the Match, he being</l>
                <l>Nobly descended, and allyed, but she</l>
                <l>Without a name, or Family, secretly</l>
                <l>He purchas'd a Divorce, to disanull</l>
                <l>His former Contract, marrying openly</l>
                <l>The Lady<persName>Violante</persName>.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Iac.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>As you sit here</l>
                <l>The Deputy of the great King, who is</l>
                <l>The Substitute of that impartiall  Judge</l>
                <l>With whom, or Wealth, or titles prevaile nothing,</l>
                <l>Grant to a much wrong'd Widow, or a Wife</l>
                <l>Your patience, with liberty to speake</l>
                <l>In her owne Cause, and let me face to face</l>
                <l>To this bad man, deliver what he is:</l>
                <l>And if my wrongs, with his ingratitude ballanc'd,</l>
                <l>Move not compassion, let me die unpittied;</l>
                <l>His teares, his oathes, his perjuries, I passe o're</l>
                <l>To thinke of them, is a disease; but death</l>
                <l>Should I repeat them. I dare not deny,</l>
                <l>(For Innocence cannot justifie what's false)</l>
                <l>But all the Advocate hath alleadged concerning</l>
                <l>His falsehod, and my shame in my consent,</l>
                <l>To be most true: But now I turne to thee,</l>
                <l>To thee <persName><roleName>Don</roleName> Henrique</persName>, and if impious Acts</l>
                <l>Have left thee blood enough to make a blush,</l>
                <l>I'll paint it on thy cheekes. Was not the wrong</l>
                <l>Sufficient to defeat me of mine honour,</l>
                <l>To leave me full of sorrow, as of want,</l>
                <l>The witnesse of thy lust, left in my womb,</l>
                <l>To testifie thy falsehood, and my shame?</l>
                <l>But now so many yeares I have conceal'd</l>
                <l>Thy most inhumane wickednesse, and won</l>
                <l>This Gentleman, to hide it from the <placeName>world</placeName></l>
                <l>To Father what was thine (for yet by <placeName>heaven</placeName>,</l>
                <l>Though in the <placeName>City</placeName>, he pas'd for my husband,</l>
                <l>He never knew me as his wife,)</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Assist.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>'Tis strange:</l>
                <l>Give him an Oath.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I gladly sweare, and truly.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Iac.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>After all this (I say) when I had borne</l>
                <l>These wrongs, with Saint-like patience, saw another</l>
                <l>Freely enjoy, what was (in Justice) mine,</l>
                <l>Yet still so tender of thy rest, and quiet,</l>
                <l>I never would divulge it, to disturb</l>
                <l>Thy peace at <placeName>home</placeName>, yet thou most barbarous,</l>
                <l>To be so carelesse of me, and my Fame,</l>
                <l>(For all respect of thine in the first step</l><note type="mansNote" resp="#formerOwner" subtype="other">Lines.</note>
                <l>To thy base lust, was lost) in open Court <stage type="business" place="right">Chess-boord and</stage></l>
                <l>To publish my disgrace? and on record, <stage type="business" place="right">men set ready.</stage></l>
                <l>To write me up an easie-yeilding wanton?</l>
                <l>I thinke can find no president: In my extreames,</l>
                <l>One comfort yet is left, that though the Law</l>
                <l>Divorce me from thy bed, and made free way</l>
                <l>To the unjust embraces of an other,</l>
                <l>It cannot yet deny that this is thy Son</l>
                <l>(Looke up <persName>Ascanio</persName> since it is come out)</l>
                <l>Is thy legitimate heire.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Iam.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Confederacie:</l>
                <l>A trick (my Lord) to cheat me; e're you give</l>
                <l>Your sentence grant me hearing.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Assist.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>New <persName>Chymera</persName>'s?</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Iam.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I am (my Lord) since he is without Issue,</l>
                <l>Or hope of any, his undoubted Heire,</l>
                <l>And this forg'd by the Advocate, to defeat me</l>
                <l>Of what the Lawes of <placeName>Spaine</placeName> confer upon me,</l>
                <l>A meere Imposture, and conspiracie</l>
                <l>Against my future fortunes,</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Assist.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>You are too bold,</l>
                <l>Speak to the Cause <persName><roleName>Don</roleName>Henrique</persName>.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Hen.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I confesse,</l>
                <l>(Thou the acknowledgement must wound mine ho<lb rend="turnover"/>nour,</l>
                <l>That all the Court hath heard touching this Cause,</l>
                <l>Or with me, or against me) is most true:</l>
                <l>The later part my Brother urg'd, expected:</l>
                <l>For what I now doe, is not out of Spleene</l>
                <l>(As he pretends) but from remorse of conscience)</l>
                <l>And to repaire the wrong that I have done</l>
                <l>To this poore woman: And I beseech your Lordship</l>
                <l>To thinke I have not so far lost my reason,</l>
                <l>To bring into my Familie, to succeed me,</l>
                <l>The stranger–Issue of anothers Bed,</l>
                <l>By proofe, this is my Son, I challenge him,</l>
                <l>Accept him, and acknowledge him, and desire</l>
                <l>By a definitive Sentence of the Court,</l>
                <l>He may be so recorded, and full powre</l>
                <l>To me, to take him home.</l>
              </lg>   
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Iac.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>A second rape</l>
                <l>To the poore remnant of Content, that's left me,</l>
                <l>If this be granted: and all my former wrongs</l>
                <l>Were but beginnings to my miseries,</l>
                <l>But this the height of all: rather then part</l>
                <l>With my <persName>Ascanio</persName>, I'll deny my oath,</l>
                <l>Professe my selfe a Strumpet, and endure</l>
                <l>What punishment soe're the Court decrees</l>
                <l>Against a wretch that hath forsworne her selfe,</l>
                <l>Or plai'd the impudent whore.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Assist.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>This tastes of passion,</l>
                <l>And that must not divert the course of Justice;</l>
                <l><persName><roleName>Don</roleName> Henrique</persName>, take your Son, with this Condition</l>
                <l>You give him maintenance, as becomes his birth,</l>
                <l>And 'twill stand with your honour to doe something</l>
                <l>For this wronged woman: I will compell nothing,</l>
                <l>But leave it to your will. Break up the Court:</l>
                <l>It is in vaine to move me; my doom's pass'd,</l>
                <l>And cannot be revok'd. —</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <stage type="exit" place="right">Exit.</stage>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Hen.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>There's your reward.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>More Causes: and such Fees. Now to my Wife,</l>
                <l>I have too long bin absent: Health to your Lordship,</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <fw type="catch" rend="italic">Asc.</fw>
            <pb n="TSC-014"
              facs="https://digital.libraries.psu.edu/digital/collection/emblem/id/4394/rec/4"/>
            <fw type="pageNum">38</fw>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Asc.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>You all look strangely, and I feare beleeve</l>
                <l>This unexpected fortune makes me proud,</l>
                <l>Indeed it do's not: I shall ever pay you</l>
                <l>The duty of a son, and honour you</l>
                <l>Next to my Father: good my Lord, for yet</l>
                <l>I dare not call you uncle, be not sad,</l>
                <l>I never shall forget those noble favours</l>
                <l>You did me being a stranger, and if ever</l>
                <l>I live to be the master of a fortune,</l><note type="mansNote" resp="#formerOwner" subtype="beReady">Bar: be ready.</note>
                <l>You shall command it.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Jam.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Since it was determi'nd</l>
                <l>I should be cozen'd, I am, glad the profit</l>
                <l>Shall fall on thee, I am too tough to melt,</l>
                <l>But something will do.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Hen.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>'Pray you take leave</l>
                <l>Of your steward (gentle Brother) the good husband</l>
                <l>That takes up all for you.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Jam.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Very well, mock on,</l>
                <l>It is your turn: I may have mine—</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <stage type="exit" place="right">Exit.</stage>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>But do not</l>
                <l>Forget us deare <persName>Ascanio</persName></l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Asc.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Do not feare it,</l>
                <l>I Every day will see you: every houre</l>
                <l>Remember you in my prayers.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Jam.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>My grief's too great</l>
                <l>To be expressed in words — —</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <stage type="exit" place="right">Exit.</stage>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Hen.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Take that and leave us,</l>
                <l>Leave us without reply, nay come back sirrah</l>
                <l>And study to forget such things as these</l>
                <l>As are not worth the knowledge.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Asc.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>O good Sir.</l>
                <l>These are bad principles—</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Hen.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Such as you must learn</l>
                <l>Now you are mine, for wealth and poverty</l>
                <l>Can hold no friendship: and what is my will</l>
                <l>You must observe and do, though good or ill.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <stage type="exit" place="right">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div xml:id="act3s4" type="scene" n="4">
            <head>
              <hi rend="italic">Scena Quarta.</hi>
            </head>
            <stage type="entrance" place="center">Enter Barolus.</stage><note type="mansNote" resp="#formerOwner" subtype="crosshatchedlines">Cross-hatched lines.</note><note type="mansNote" resp="#formerOwner" subtype="beReady">Amar be ready</note>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Where is my wife? 'fore <placeName>heaven</placeName>, I have done won</l>
                <l>Done mighty things to day, my <persName>Amaranta</persName>,</l>
                <l>My heart rejoyces at my wealthy Gleanings,</l>
                <l>A rich litigious Lord I love to follow,</l>
                <l>A Lord that builds his happinesse on brawlings,</l>
                <l>O 'tis a blessed thing to have rich Clyents,</l>
                <l>Why, wife I say, how fares my studious Pupill?</l>
                <l>Hard at it still? ye are too violent</l>
                <l>All things must have their rests, they will not last els</l>
                <l>Come out and breathe.</l><note type="mansNote" resp="#formerOwner" subtype="crosshatchedlines">Cross-hatched lines.</note>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <stage type="business" place="right">Leandro within</stage>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lean.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I do beseech you pardon me</l>
                <l>I am deeply in a sweet point Sir,</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I'le instruct ye: <stage type="entrance" place="right">Enter Amaranta.</stage></l><note type="mansNote" resp="#formerOwner" subtype="crosshatchedlines">Cross-hatched lines.</note>
                <l>I say take breath, seek health first, then your study,</l>
                <l>O my sweet soul I have brought thee golden birds <placeName>home</placeName></l>
                <l>Birds in abundance. I have done strange wonders:</l>
                <l>There's more a hatching too.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Am.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Have ye done good husband?</l>
                <l>Then 'tis a good day spend</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Good enough chicken,</l>
                <l>I have spread the nets o'th'law,to catch rich booties,</l>
                <l>And they come flttering in: how do's my Pupil?</l>
                <l>My modest thing, hast thou yet spoken to him?</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Am.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Am I past by his <placeName>chamber</placeName> I might see him,</l><note type="mansNote" resp="#formerOwner" subtype="other">Moore with a chese bord</note>
                <l>But he is so bookish,</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>And so bashfull too,</l>
                <l>I faith he is, before he will speak, he will starve there</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Am.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I pitie him a little.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>So do I too.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Am.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>And if he please to take the aire o'th' <placeName>gardens</placeName></l>
                <l>Or walk i'th'<placeName>inward roomes</placeName>, so he molest not—</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>He shall not trouble thee, he dare not speak to thee <stage type="entrance" place="center">Enter Moore with Chesse-board</stage></l>
                <l>Bring out the Chesse-board,—come let's have a game<lb rend="turnunder"/>wife,</l>
                <l>I'le try your masterie, you say you are cunning</l>
              </lg>  
            </sp>  
            <sp>
              <speaker>Am.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>As learned as ye are (Sir) I shall beat ye</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <stage type="entrance" place="center">Enter Leandro.</stage><note type="mansNote" resp="#formerOwner" subtype="crosshatchedlines">Cross-hatched lines.</note>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Ba.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Here he steales out, put him not out of countenance</l>
                <l>'Prethee look another way, he will be gone else</l>
                <l>Walk and refresh your self, I'l be with you presently,</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lean.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I'le take the aire a little.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>'Twill be healthfnll.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Am.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Will ye be there? then here? Ile spare ye that man,</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lean.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>'Would I were so neare too, and a mate fitting.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>A.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>What thinke ye (, Sir) to this? have at your Knight now</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>'Twas subtilly playd: your Queen lies at my service</l>
                <l>Pre thee look off, he is ready to pop in again</l>
                <l>Look off I say, do'st thou not see how he blushes?</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Am.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I do not blast him:</l><note type="mansNote" resp="#formerOwner" subtype="beReady">moore be ready</note>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lean.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>You are a blessed man that may so have her.</l><note type="mansNote" resp="#formerOwner" subtype="crosshatchedlines">Cross-hatched lines.</note>
                <l>Oh that I might play with her—</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <stage type="business" place="right">knock within</stage>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Who's there? I come, you cannot escape me now wife</l>
                <l>I come, I come,</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <stage type="business" place="right">knock</stage><note type="mansNote" resp="#formerOwner" subtype="crosshatchedlines">Cross-hatched lines.</note>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lean.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Most blessed hand that calls him.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Play quickly wife.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Am.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>'Pray ye give leave to think, Sir.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <stage type="entrance" place="center">Enter Moore.</stage><note type="mansNote" resp="#formerOwner" subtype="crosshatchedlines">Cross-hatched lines.</note>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Moore</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>An honest neighbour that dwells hard by (Sir)</l>
                <l>Would fain speak with your worship about businesse.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lean.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>The <persName>devil</persName> blow him off.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Play.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Am.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I will study:</l>
                <l>For if you beat me thus, you will still laugh at me—</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <stage type="business" place="right">knock</stage><note type="mansNote" resp="#formerOwner" subtype="crosshatchedlines">Cross-hatched lines.</note>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>He knocks again; I cannot stay. <persName>Leandro</persName></l>
                <l>'Pray thee come near.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lean.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I am well (Sir) here,</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Come hither:</l>
                <l>Be not afraid but come.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Am.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Here's none will bite (Sir)</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lean.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>God forbid Lady.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Am.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>'Pray come nearer.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lean.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Yes forsooth.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>'Pre thee observe these men: just as they stand here</l>
                <l>And see this Lady, do not alter 'em,</l>
                <l>And be not partiall, Pupill.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lean.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>No indeed Sir.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Let her not move a pawn, I'le come back presently</l>
                <l>Nay you shall know I am a Conquerour.</l>
                <l>Have an eye Pupill——</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <stage type="exit" place="right">Exit.</stage>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Am.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Can ye play at Chesse Sir?</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lean.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>A little Lady.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Am.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>But you cannot tell me</l>
                <l>How to avoid this Mate, &amp; win the Game too</l>
                <l>Ha's noble eyes: ye dare not friend me so farre.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lean.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I dare do any thing that's in mans power, Lady,</l>
                <fw type="catch">To</fw>
                <pb n="TSC-015"
                  facs="https://digital.libraries.psu.edu/digital/collection/emblem/id/4395/rec/4"/>
                <fw type="pageNum">39</fw>
                <l>To be a friend to such a noble beauty.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Am.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>This is no Lawyers language: I pray ye tell me,</l>
                <l>Whether may I remove, Ye see I am set round?</l>
                <l>To avoid my husband.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lean.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I shall tell ye happily.</l>
                <l>But happily you will not be instructed.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Am.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Yes, and I thank ye too, shall I move this man?</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lean.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Those are unseemly: move one can serve ye</l>
                <l>Can honour ye, can love ye.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Am.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>'Pray ye tell quickly</l>
                <l>He will return and then</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lean.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I'le tell ye instantly</l>
                <l>Move me, and I wil move any way to serve ye</l>
                <l>Move your heart this way ( Lady)</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Am.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>How?</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lean.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>'Pray ye heare me.</l>
                <l>Behold the sport of Love, when he is imperious</l>
                <l>Behold the slave of Love</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Am.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Move my Queen this way?</l><note type="mansNote" resp="#formerOwner" subtype="beReady">bartolus be ready</note>
                <l>Sure, he's some worthy man: then if he hedge me</l>
                <l>Or here to open him.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lean.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Do but behold me</l>
                <l>If there be pity in you, do but view me,</l>
                <l>But view the misery I have undertaken</l>
                <l>For you the povertie.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Am.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>He will come presently.</l>
                <l>Now play your best Sir, though I loose this Rook here</l>
                <l>Yet I get Libertie.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lean.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I'le seize your fair hand</l>
                <l>And warm it with a hundred, hundred kisses</l>
                <l>The God of love warm your desires but equal</l>
                <l>That shall play my game now.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Am.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>What do you mean Sir?</l>
                <l>Why do you stop me?</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lean.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>That ye may intend me.</l>
                <l>The time ha's blest us both: Love bid us use it.</l>
                <l>I am a Gentleman nobly descended:</l>
                <l>Young to invite your Love, rich to maintain it.</l>
                <l>I bring a whole heart to ye, thus I give it,</l>
                <l>And to those burning altars thus I offer,</l>
                <l>And thus divine lips, where perpetuall Spring grows.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Am.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Take that, ye are too saucy.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lean.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>How proud Lady?</l>
                <l>Strike my deserts?</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Am.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I was too blame.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <stage type="entrance" place="center">Enter Bartolus.</stage><note type="mansNote" resp="#formerOwner" subtype="crosshatchedlines">Cross-hatched lines.</note>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>What wife, there?</l>
                <l>Heaven keep my <placeName>house</placeName> from thieves.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lean.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I am wretched:</l>
                <l>Opened, discovered, lost to my wishes.</l>
                <l>I shall be whooted at.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>What noise was this (wife?)</l>
                <l>Why dost thou smile?</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lean.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>This proud thing will betray me.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Why these lie here? what anger (deare?)</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Am,</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Why none, Sir,</l>
                <l>Onely a chance your pupill said he plaid well,</l>
                <l>And so indeed he do's: he undertook for ye</l>
                <l>Because I would not sit so long time idle</l>
                <l>I made my Liberty, avoided your mate,</l>
                <l>And he again as cunningly endangered me,</l>
                <l>Indeed he put me strangely to it. When presently</l>
                <l>Hearing you come, and having broke his ambush too</l>
                <l>Having the second time brought off my Queen fair,</l>
                <l>I rose o'th' sudden smilingly to shew ye,</l>
                <l>My apron caught the Chesse-board, and the men,</l>
                <l>And there the noise was.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Thou art grown a Master,</l><note type="mansNote" resp="#formerOwner" subtype="other">Act</note>
                <l>For all this, I shall beat ye.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lean.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Or I, Lawyer,</l>
                <l>For now I love her more, 'twas a neat answer,</l>
                <l>And it hangs by a mighty hope, I thank her</l>
                <l>She gave my pate a sound knock that it rings yet,</l>
                <l>But you shall have a sounder if I live Lawyer,</l>
                <l>My heart akes yet I would not be in that fear—</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I am glad ye are a ‘gamester, Sir, sometimes</l>
                <l>For recreation we two shall fight hard at it,</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Am.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>He will prove too hard for me,</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lean.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I hope he shall do,</l>
                <l>But your Ches-board is too hard for my head, line that <lb rend="turnover"/>good Lady,</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I have been attoning, two most wrangling neig<lb rend="turnunder"/>bours,</l>
                <l>They had no money, therefore I made even</l>
                <l>Come, let's go in, and eat, truly I am hungry.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lean.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I have eaten already, I must intreat your pardon</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>Do as ye please, we shall expect ye at supper.</l>
                <l>He ha's got a little heart, not it seems handsomly,</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Am.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>You'l get no little head, if I do not look to ye.</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker>Lean.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>If ever I do catch thee again thou vanity—</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker> rend="italic">Am.</speaker>
              <lg>
                <l>I was too blame to be so rash, I am sorie—</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <stage type="exit" place="right">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
      </div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
